He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st Inoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits.
Angel.
demons and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this
spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every
day life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show, focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of
the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
A good evening, you aphologists, paranormal investigators, and psychics, psychotics.
You are listening to Coast to Coast AFM, and it's episode 123.
My co-host Father Stephen Diyun renowned KJV-onlyist and uncredited subject of the
Breesharp single, David Ducovny is with me straight from the swamp in Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm finding it at-
F-
other Andrew Stephen Damick in Emma's Pennsylvania broadcasting live from the arc of the covenant
experience where no one's going to catch us with our eyes closed. And we are once once again.
I don't know why they keep putting us on after that guy. I know. I'd like, I've said this before,
I don't want to be associated with him. He doesn't know what he's talking about.
Probably a heretic and you know, the end of the show, they give out that email address.
He never answers those emails.
I don't think he even reads them.
True facts.
True facts?
Well, if you good listeners are listening to us live,
you can call us at a552372346
and someone will answer the phone.
Someone will answer the phone.
And who will it be?
And starting in the second half of the show,
it will be Mike, don't tell Ken Hamd again,
who will be taking those calls.
But first a word from our sponsor.
This episode of The Lord of Spirits is sponsored by the upcoming feature film,
El Tanto Por Cristo.
A Texas coastline, a brotherhood of monks,
inching their way towards St. Edward.
El Tanto Por Cristo is the first Orthodox,
full-length feature film made in America,
a cinematic pilgrimage with one night only events in theaters across the country.
The National Roadshow begins on October 6 in Dallas, Texas at the historic Texas theater.
From there the film travels city by city.
one night at a time. Executive producer Jonathan Peugeot calls it
dangerous in the best way. David Lowry says it looks like Tarkovsky by way of
Texas. And Frederika Matthews Green calls it
phenomenal, truly a work of art. From award-winning filmmaker Josh
David Jordan and Emmy nominated composer Michael Puraskevas.
This tour is underway with new dates being added.
Tickets and showtimes visit L-TontoPoorCristo.com and if you'd like to
to bring the film to your own city.
Click the host tab to learn more. That's el tanto por Cristo.com.
Are you going to address the elephant in the room there?
What is the elephant in the room?
The divergence of movie taste between yourself and Jonathan Pejo.
We have gotten a lot of contact about that, that's for sure.
Chris, he's not the one that said this particular film looks like Tarkovsky by way of Texas.
No. He said it was dangerous in the best way.
He said it was dangerous in the best way.
That's right.
Just rubbing salt in the wound there, father.
I don't know.
I felt like someone had to say something.
Someone has said something.
You're the only one for the last week who hasn't.
Until now.
Right.
But you know, our visitors at home, they were yelling at their devices of various kinds,
not their videos because, you know, there have been news for me.
No one listens to it on a radio.
head.
memes made. Yeah, yeah. This is tonight. Tonight kids. This is our fifth anniversary episode. And this
episode on ancient flood stories is our special gift to you. So, Father Steven, do you have some kind
of nostalgic nostalgic feelings stretching back to 2020? You'd like to share with the kids at home.
The only really good thing about 2020 was that you could you could be a recluse and not be
with
down upon for it. You had to get away with it. You had cover to just never leave the house
and do anything. There's a brief while where everyone was as you are. Yes, everyone just left
real alone in my whole. Yes, but also I do want to say this this episode is our anniversary gift to
you. If you would like to give an anniversary gift to us, I will accept cash. Wow. I never thought
you'd be so brazen.
I'm not saying they should said cash. I'm just saying you would accept it. I would accept it. Right. I'll cash the check. That's all I'm saying. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Yeah.
No one needs to send me one. But if someone does, I'll cash it. That's all I'm saying.
Just say it as a man.
Well, 2020.
Because I don't think that goes without saying this is never I never thought we both see this this moment.
What, the fifth anniversary?
The fifth anniversary?
50th anniversary of being born, all that kind of stuff, all at once.
I mean, I thought I'd make it to 50.
It is a good moment to end the show.
What do you think?
What were you up to that you thought you wouldn't make it to 50?
I know.
It just seems like an impossibly large number for human beings to ever achieve.
And now this is a good moment in the show.
Remember, we're going to, we're going to, the last episodes,
going to be the one we do live at the conference.
We're just not telling anybody.
Oh, that's right.
That's right.
That's going to be the big special secret surprises are telling me where the
says
over. Yeah. All right. All right. Well, make sure you don't see that after we start recording
though. Yeah. No. Yeah. Once the show goes live. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. We'll keep
that safe. Yeah. So I mean, we're going to talk about the flood, which flood, where,
in what language, the flood, the definite article is at work. Yes. See, this is another
moment to trigger Jonathan Peugeot that we've actually discovered. Almost every person who
works for the symbolic work.
world at some point has their house flooded.
So it's true.
It's true. Did you know that?
I know someone who I don't believe has had their house flooded.
Oh, yet, but they made Albee jinx because they live in southern Louisiana.
And it's hurricane season.
So I mean, y'all exactly don't have a low water table there.
And that's what I'm saying.
You may write the jinx on a whole family.
They do muzzle children like they do in the
Orleans is all mausoleums there as well. Mostly. Yeah. Nice. Very, very, uh,
picturesque and creepy and all the rest, all the best kinds of ways. Yeah. Well,
I do live across the street from a cemetery with large, beautiful bay windows looking out
upon it. Hmm. So, but see, the ghosts aren't at the cemetery. The ghosts are wherever the people
died. Oh, is that how it works? Yeah, that's why I don't understand why people are spooked out at
Like the bodies are there, the ghosts are back, you know,
ancient Sumerian ghosts.
I mean, probably not, you know,
they're probably maybe some dead nephilum floating around here and there.
But I think they're more towards the video shops in New Orleans than here.
Yeah.
So should we talk about the topic of the episode?
How about that?
Okay.
Okay, I can tell in the background.
your mind was really working on a segue to try to get from
like the two-marrying ghost thing was kind of a lame attempt.
You were working out something better.
That's what I had.
What can I do?
Yeah, so, yeah, the flood related.
Flood related.
You just, you know, a few too many steps to make it a smooth
segue.
Like, good would have been, you know, like, well,
and I imagine that like a hospice center would have a flood
of ghosts, right?
Nice.
I mean also land.
but pretty good. Yeah, but pithy. Yeah. Anyway, yes. So there's a story in Genesis chapter 6 through 9 about a flood.
Which weirdly, we have never done a flood episode until now. We have never actually done an episode.
It's like we've never done an Enoch episode, even though apparently all of our Apple reviews, that's all we talk about.
This is so sweet.
There's nothing except about Ynac.
Every episode is a book of Eden.
episode. Yeah, especially the ones where we don't even mention it. Yeah. So we've never,
we've never actually talked about stuff that happened right before the flood, leading up to the flood,
after the flood. Yep. Yeah. Around the flood. But now we're going to stop talking around the issue
and address it directly. I keep claiming, even though we haven't yet, and how long does this
episode going on already. 10 minutes. 10 minutes okay.
So Genesis 6 through 9 is not the only place where the story of the flood, the definite article as it were, is told.
And so we're going to start out tonight by talking about some of the other places, specifically the other places in Mesopotamia.
All right, we'll end between the rivers.
Now if you're watching a horrible Bible document...
documentary. I was about to say on cable television, but for you kids, that's like
streaming, except you can't control it. It still exists by the way.
The cable TV still exists. Yeah, if you're watching with those documentaries,
they will say something dumb usually like the book of Genesis plagiarizes the
story of the flood, yeah, as if it was like a school assignment.
And the author of Dennis is like Gpt back in those days,
turned into a bunch of stuff he stole from from
Atra Haasis, right?
You know, which is just absurd, right, on the face, right?
Like, we're gonna get it.
Most of what we're gonna be talking about tonight has to do with the
relationship between these stories and how these stories function.
But the idea that it is quote unquote, please
is of course stupid, right? Like the idea that the Bible is an original work of fiction,
there are certain presuppositions behind it that we do not accept. So we're going to start with
even though it's not the oldest one we have.
by a little bit. We're going to start with the what's called the Sumerian flood story.
And it's called the Sumerian flood story because it is on tablets that are written in the Sumerian language.
And because it is, it seems to be part of a larger story, we're just missing the part before and
and potentially the part F.
the flood story itself, right? And so we don't have a name, we don't know or we don't know the name of
whatever the larger work would have been. We just know this is a tablet with a flood story
in Samarian. Now you can actually go see this tablet. I have. Right here in the United States of
America. Yes, it's it's in Philadelphia in Penn Slot.
Yeah, yeah, Philadelphia version 2.0 is it were
At the the Penn University of Pennsylvania, you know, you pen museum, which if you're in the Philly area everybody
It is really actually a very good museum worth seeing with lots of
super ancient and less ancient stuff
So and you can at least see the Sumerian flood story tablet. Yeah, yeah, just something all by itself
I also recommend the the
museum of art as well you can go see the big rocky statue out in the front steps.
That's what people do there. So if he's with the rocky statue.
It's slightly more recent. Yep. Yep. The movie rocky.
So we know when this tablet was made, right? We know when a read was set to clay as a tour.
and that is in 1600 BC.
And we know where, was in the city of Nipur, which is in the region of Sumeria.
Was there a Sumeria as such in the days?
So yeah, we have to disambiguate Sumer and Sumeria a little bit.
Right? So when we hear Sumerian, we probably first think of ancient Sumer like the culture.
culture.
Sort of the earliest, what are the earliest layers of written human culture going back to
least
3000 before that BC, right
That's a particular civilization in culture. There is a Sumerian language that comes from that civilization
Sumerian language is a language isolate meaning it is not related to any other languages
It is not a submitted language.
It is not an Indo-European language, it is its own thing.
And Sumer is also the name of that region, which is basically southern Mesopotamia.
So today, in modern times, basically southern Iraq, a little bit of southern Iran.
that region was sumer and then the northern region of Mesopotamia was a cod.
And a cod is where the accadian language comes from and the accadian language is sort of the
Ur Semitic language
Not of the city of war
But the other sort of the way that sans grit. Yeah, sans grit is a root language for Indo-European languages
Accadian is sort of a root language for Semitic languages. Yeah. Yeah
And so even though in 1600 BC in Nepal, right, 1600 BC, we're talking about during the Babylonian Empire, the original one.
In the middle of Babylon. I conquered that whole region.
Yeah, second millennium BC, right. Cities in Akkad and cities in Sumer at various points in ancient history dominated each other.
like we talked about earlier around 2000 BC in the or three period.
We were talking about Abraham.
That was the Sumerian Renaissance, and that was where Sumer and Ura in particular re-roads
to prominence and was sort of dominated the northern area of Akat.
And so it went back and forth between northern and southern regions.
But so even though this is a period of time where Akat is more dominant and most of the
the
we have being written during that time or being written in a cadian, this is written in Sumerian.
That said, because of the time, likely that it's written, the Sumerian that it's written in
is sort of heavily influenced, grammatically, especially in the verbs, by a cadian, by Babylonian
indicating. Yeah, so this is like when you read, you know,
but some metasisms are even occasionally maybe helpful.
in the Bible with phrases like, and it came to pass,
which is clearly a translation of something.
We're so used to it now, we don't tend to think of it that way,
but it is or the word walk being used
to refer to the way that you live your life.
Yeah.
And we'll go to nerdy on it.
What?
It do is a Greek translation of him.
and Hebrew, right?
Like, yeah.
Right.
Low or behold or whatever.
Or wham.
So, which tells us a couple of things, right?
And one of those is that people highly suspect and we'll see more about this as we go on
tonight, that even though this is being written in Sumerian, that there is a Babylonian
version of
this story in view for the person who's writing it.
He may not be directly translating from a cadient to Sumerian.
He may not be, right, he could be, for example, making a copy of an earlier Sumerian translation.
He could be just sort of putting this version of the story together himself and just he
personally.
New both languages and so his Sumerian was kind of accented by his Acadian because Acadian was his first language
That happens, right
But there is there is likely some Babylonian version of the story that was familiar
that lies sort of behind
This Sumerian tablet
And so basically what we get in this tablet in this story is
that there are two groups of gods. There's the great gods and the lesser gods. And this is a
constant through all these stories, but this is also a constant through ancient Erystrom paganism.
And even into Greek and Roman paganism. And even I think it's a Norse paganism,
There are sort of these two tears, right?
You've got, in Greek paganism, you've got sort of God's proper...
and then you've got sort of nymphs and spirits and things, right? They're sort of a lower
ranked. So you have the same thing. You have greater and lesser gods in ancient Near Eastern.
View, the greater gods are obviously like the most high god and then usually gods associated
with elements of the cosmos, right?
Sun, moon, things like that.
And then the lesser gods are usually gods who in general, this is a generalization, so they're exceptions, but
generally gods associated with various
human activities like craftsmen and
things like that, right? Maybe associated with that kind of thing or the lesser.
Local territorial gods. Yeah, those are usually the lower ranked ones, right? Because and you can see how that would happen, right?
obviously right the sun is in one category and
you know, finding water in your field
is in a different category of things.
That oak tree.
Yeah.
So the, the, in the Sumerian flood story,
the great gods decide they're gonna destroy the world.
And it begins kind of abruptly.
This is why we're pretty sure there was some kind of story
proceeding at probably some kind of creation story
because the other versions of this story include
including the one in Genesis, obviously, the story of the flood is sort of preceded by a
story of the creation of humanity. We're just sort of informed as the tablet starts
that, you know, by the setting and everything that this is after the establishment of cities,
the establishment of kingship, right? So there's already some human history that's happened
that isn't narrated on this tablet. So we assume, okay, there was, there was a previous
tablet or previous tablets.
telling those stories. But so they assign to destroy the world and there it begins with this there's kind of a conflict between the God Nintur who is the God of creation. This is another reason why we think there was a creation story
in a tablet before this because the God who created people doesn't want to see
them all get wiped out but kind of gets overruled by everybody else.
Right. And so the main character, the sort of hero character of the Sumerian flood story is
Xeasudra, sometimes referred to just by the abbreviated Soudra
in the text. And Xeasudra is Sumerian for he of long life,
the long
lived guy. It's kind of a chicken egg issue here. Yeah. Yeah. Well, I mean, I suppose you
could name a child that is sort of a blessing or a desire or wish for the aspirational name.
Yeah. And he was both. He's a king. We'll see why in a second. And he's also a priest of the
uh, Sumerian God Enke.
Hmm.
So he is a priest king himself.
He is a king because he is the son of Ubar Tutu.
It's a great name.
Although I know a relation to Archbishop Desmond Tutu.
Ha ha ha.
Let's just say I don't suggest naming your kids this, but...
Who has Ubar Tutu, Father Stephen?
Ha ha.
Ubar Tutu was the king of Shrupaq.
As everyone knows.
Which is kind of an awesome city name.
Yes, it is.
Yeah, I mean, sure a pack.
I mean, this is one of the cities that you can build in the civilization games if you're
playing Sumeria.
Well, there you go.
And if you go, this is a different text, right?
But if you go and consult the Sumerian Kings list, which we've talked about before on
the show a few times, the Sumerian Kings list lists all the Kings, all the Sumerian Kings
before the flood and then after the flood, right?
And Ubar Tutu is on the Sumerian Kings list.
He is listed as the last king of Shura pack before the flood.
So the Sumerian flood story tablet is working with a guy who is otherwise known from Sumerian text.
And the Sumerian Kings list is actually much older.
Right. So this is kind of a known thing.
Also, for the record, I know I mentioned this before but this is an example. I mentioned this before
show when we were talking about the like the genealogy of Kane and the genealogy of Seth,
you know, we've got all the long lives of people, you know, and your local atheist is like,
oh, dumb, he lived nine hundred sixty nine years. That's got nothing on the Samaritan Kings list.
Aren't they like hundreds of thousands?
According to the Samaritan Kings list, Ubar Tutu was the king of ShuraPak for eighteen thousand
900 years.
I mean, that's some continuity of government right there.
And that is rain was cut off by the flood.
So he would have kept going.
Yeah, if not for this whole flood thing, right?
But so that gives you an idea.
We've also talked about, and you may have noticed, 18,900 is evenly divisible by 60.
that the numbers are based on base safety X-T, double-oddion map.
So, Zia Sudra, this priest king, rather than waiting around, however many more thousand
years it would have taken to assume his father's throne, gathers his wives and a bunch of
animals onto a boat, and together they survive the flood.
But we have of the text, right?
And there may have been more tablets, more text that...
explained more, right? Does it sort of tell us how he knew a flood was coming? Yeah. Right.
I mean, it might be implied with him being a priest of Inky, that maybe Inky tipped him off,
or that Ninters, or you got a rule out of tipped him off or just got a boat at hand and notice,
wow, it sure has been raining. Yeah. A lot. Rain doesn't seem to be stopping. Let me get my boat
I'm going to load on the animals and my wives.
But it...
kind of the implication of what we have is that the focus is on like he sort of survives
through his own ingenuity.
Yeah.
He's a really smart guy.
He knows what he's doing.
Because every say that because after the flood then the gods are sort of impressed by
the fact that he managed to survive.
Like why are we trying to kill everybody, but this guy is guy.
Pretty sneaky.
Right. Um.
So they settled him in the land of Dilmun, where the sun rises.
We don't know exactly where that is.
And in fact, it may not be an actual place.
Like it may be talking about literally where the sun rises.
Because we'll see some of these sort of hero figures get demonized after the flood.
But so that's all we've got.
We've just got, you know, we don't have the whole frame.
story and everything of the Sumerian flood story. Now probably in the probably the most
well-known version of the flood story in the ancient Near East as far as we can tell.
And the reason I'm saying as far as we can tell is important. And this is important in
a broad range of topics.
Far beyond.
the flood story in terms of our knowledge of the ancient world. Our knowledge of the ancient world
is based on what has come down and survived to us. Which is a tiny tiny tiny tiny
It's so sad, tiny fraction.
Even of the well-known stuff.
Right?
Even of the well-known stuff. I'm not just talking about like who knows how many flood stories there were in ancient Mesopotamia
Which true how who knows how many variations there were over the centuries right of the flood story
but
Things like and much later things like we don't have most of Plato's writings
Hmm
We know from ancient catalogs that Plato not only wrote a bunch of dialogues that we don't have anymore
but he wrote treatises like Aristotle.
And we don't have any of them.
Likewise Aristotle, according to these ancient lists, wrote dialogues.
In addition to his treatises, we don't have any of Aristotle's dialogues.
And those are, I mean, Plato and Aristotle, that's like his famous as you get in terms
of preserving ancient literature, right?
And we have a tiny fraction of that.
Now, what we've talked about this before with like the church fathers, right?
Of course, we believe that the Holy Spirit is guiding the church, okay?
But we're not talking about the church fathers.
We're talking about like the speeches of Cicero.
There's enough, right?
I'm not denying that there's enough behind Providence involved.
But yes, in God's Providence, we have the things God wants us to have
that will rediscover things if he wants us to rediscover them.
BAH!
But the point I'm making is about us making claims about the past.
Yeah. Right. Us saying, you know, uh,
this was the most common, or this was the most popular,
or there were no fill in the blank in a particular time.
Yeah, we need to state these things positively like, okay,
this piece of evidence says this. Right.
But even even
cases of evidence obviously are capable of multiple interpretations.
Yeah.
Or it could be a minority report that we don't even know about.
Right.
But most was going on.
And so your red flag should go up.
This is one of the problems with those Bible documentaries.
Right.
What you love to watch.
No, which I am impelled to.
Okay.
It's like the show Dexter.
I have an abusive relationship with it.
I
I am disappointed in almost every season,
but the next one comes on and I watch it nonetheless.
And I start to think halfway through,
oh, this one's actually pretty good.
And then I'm crushed once again.
Same way with Bible documentaries.
It's twisted, masochistic compulsion.
But, yeah, the Bible documentaries,
they always say things very confidently.
Right, they always just say, right, like, you know,
this, you know.
Oh, we found a copy of the Gospel of Judas. Now don't mind that the church fathers had already talked about this. Right. We already knew this was a thing that existed. We kind of knew what it was about. But hey, we finally found a copy. This is going to shake Christianity to its core. Yeah. This has been suppressed for all of these many centuries. But yeah, all nonsense. Right.
Like, right, you don't find that in, right?
Like to make tiny modest...
claims actual scholars write like whole journal articles. Right, right, like 12 page journal
article with like 137 footnotes to try and argue that, yeah, there actually should be a definite
article in front of this word in this text, right? That's the kind of things you get in
and like real scholarship.
And in that.
that journal article they'll like acknowledge that,
you know, here are the other possibilities
if my thesis isn't correct.
But that's not what you get from a lot of people.
You get people making just very confident assertions.
Right.
So we think,
ultra-hossi-hossi-sepic is the most popular version
and we think that, here's why we think that.
We think that because...
because we've got the text in multiple languages,
in multiple copies across a period of several centuries.
Now, maybe there was some way more popular version
and we just haven't found it.
Or it may be that the Sumerian flood myth
or the one we're gonna talk about after after houses, right?
We're actually way more popular.
It's just for whatever reason.
and we found fewer copies.
Right, we can't know for sure.
There's literally no way to know for sure,
barring a time machine.
And even then, you'd have to do a lot of time traveling
to different places in different centuries
and interview lots of people to find out which was the most popular.
Right, but our best guess,
Autorhossus EPIC, this particular story,
which is a longer story that includes within a flood story,
We
This endured this basic story endured over a period of centuries.
It was translated in a different languages.
We found at least copies of at least parts of it in several different geographical locations,
dating to those different centuries.
And so generally that would suggest that this is a very popular and given the
POSITY OF FINDS, like we don't even know what the full text of the
and flood myth was we believe based on that that that Autorhossus this was sort of the
the main version of the story for most people of Babylonian and even later Assyrian culture.
The Autorhossus epic proper was written in a Kadean
the primary tablets of the tech.
that we have date to the 17th century BC. So that's the 1600s BC, which again is the Babylonian Empire,
the original one. So it being an Akkadian not surprising. We have the beginning of the text as part
this and so we actually have the scribes name which was EPIC IA.
another not that we used with epinema or the girl from there.
This is possibly the most popular elevator music in in cinematics in film.
Yes.
Yeah.
Not necessarily in real life, but in film.
Yes.
Yeah.
I don't think I've ever heard the girl from epinema in an elevator.
Except in movies.
No.
And I am now of the age where sadly I'm like at the supermarket.
I'm like, wow, they're playing.
really good music. And we found this copy made by Ipecchaya. Also I'm confused with Ipecac.
Or Yippee Cayet. Yes. No finish that sentence. Yeah. I won't. At the at the it was part of the
Library.
at Sipar, which is another Babylonian city. Now, that said, there's an important
chunk of the flood story that was missing. We've had a library of Sipar that was
rediscovered recently and by recently, I mean this this millennium, this century,
the 21st
century, like 20 years ago, by Irving Finkel.
Yeah.
And when I say, old Irving Finkel discovered it, I don't mean he was in a rack, digging
the dirt and turned it up.
He was going through a big rack of accadian clay kudeiform tablets at the British Museum,
most of which were like grocery lists and trade documents and stuff.
and low and behold he found a tablet from the atroha
Yeah, I'd have to say by the way, if you guys have never like looked up Irving Finko, he's
I mean, he's still living.
He's still living still kicking and doing his thing.
There's lots of videos of him on YouTube and he is incredibly entertaining and interesting
to this.
He's interesting.
He has a very mellow British accent.
Yeah, yeah.
And there's a there's a video of him teaching someone how to play the Royal Game of
War.
We're sure everyone's going to need to watch that if you're going to participate in
our Royal Game of War Tournament at the-
He is a big, he is a big proponent of people learning to read
Cuniiform, which is an odd cause to soldier for, but it is his
because he loves, he loves his literature.
He loves making finds like this that he wants more people to
carry on that work, right?
Because there are these racks and racks of clay tablets, most of
which are not super important, but a few of which may be very
import.
like this. And not enough people to go through and read them and find out what they are.
But so we have a much more full picture just in the last decade and a half or so based on
the work of Irving Finkl about this. We also have, as I mentioned, we have pieces of the
the octahosis epic.
So this one is the one in the 17th century.
by Ippic Gaya is the old Babylonian text. That's how it's referred to. There is also we have
an ugeritic tablet from Ugarit. We've talked about a Garait before on the show. That's from a few
centuries later that is translated into Ugaritic. We have a middle Babylonian version from later in
the Babylonian Empire before it's collapse, and then we have two
different Assyrian copies, like the Assyrians in the Bible,
like 8th century BC. So that's 900 years after Ipakaia, right? We have two copies
from the library at Nineveh. So that's what I meant by this seems to have been around a while,
right? It seems to have kind of endured as a version of the story. Now as we said,
The Autohausus epic is this big epic story with Autohausus as the main character, right?
Sort of like the epic of Gilgamesh that we're going to talk about next.
But it includes within it a flood story.
And in the flood story, you may see some familiar themes to what we already saw in the Samarian flood story.
So once again, we have greater gods and lesser gods.
But of course we have the beginning of this story,
which means...
we have the story of the creation of humanity that leads into the flood, right?
So we have sort of a better scope here.
And so there's no humans, there's just the greater gods of the lesser gods.
And so the greater gods make the lesser gods do all the work.
Typical?
Yeah, just push them around, bullium, big brother, little brother.
They're gonna do all the work.
The lesser gods get tired of doing all the work.
work. And so they decide to create humanity as a slave race to do all of their work.
Okay, that's that's the inspiring story of the creation of humanity.
I know it's amazing. You know, if you read the actual story of how humanity is created
and a lot of these pagan myths, it's not great. It's not great. Right. It is a stark contrast
With humanity we made in the image of God as the crown of creation in Genesis.
Yeah, I mean, my favorite one, and this just might be a little bit of ethnocentrism on my part, but my favorite one is the Baltic human creation myth, which is the where the most high high god is kind of walking along any sort of like spitting.
And he didn't notice that his spit hit the ground and sank in and turned into humans.
And that was literally you just talking to Louge.
Yeah.
Well, yeah, you later Babylonian, you've got Marduk, you know, killing his mom and her blood falls on the ground and turns into
Yeah, um, not great. But in the after-hossis epic, right, these lesser gods who don't
do all the work, they pick one of their number, Wei Elu, who's one of the lesser gods,
and they just kill him. Yeah. And they make humanity out of his carcass. They're like,
we need a slave race. Where are we going to get one? I know. Let's kill Wei Elu. Hey, guys,
Can we talk about this, Risa?
Yeah, he's true, the short straw.
Apparently.
Right.
And so then, our hero, of course, as you might expect from the name of the epic, is
Atrahasis.
Yeah.
Atrahasis and Akkadian means the most wise one, the wise guy.
He is a priest of the God, Aya.
Aya is the Akkadian equivalent of the God Enki.
Oh, so this is like our suger friend from the suger.
Yeah, who he just saw.
the blood story. And so, Enlil, who at this point is the most high god for the Babylonians,
he and the other great gods decided to destroy the world. Right? Much like we saw in the Samaritan
blood story, but we get a little more detail as to why. And the reason we're told why, in the
the other House is epic is that
Humans are gotten too noisy and so the gods can't sleep.
There's this horrible racket coming from Earth all the time.
And what this is aimed at as we'll see is the story kind of unfolds as the idea is that there's
too many humans. Yeah. Right. We made these humans to do our slave work, right? Do our slave labor.
But now there's too many of them and they're becoming a nuisance, right? It's like
in Southern Louisiana.
know you know. And so they decide, yeah, we're just going to wipe them out. And interestingly,
sort of inserted into the text here are a series of spells to get your baby to be quiet.
Because it says that crying babies in particular irritate the gods.
Wow, by not winning them sleep.
Wow.
So the next time people in your...
church complain about babies making noise. You could tell them they're acting like pagan demons.
There you go. That'll win them over.
So, but that's sort of inserted here, right? It's just like, hey, by the way, right? Here's some spells to get your baby to be quiet.
I do not recommend engaging in sorcery to quiet your baby down.
Um.
Just so that doesn't get you know you never know what's gonna end up as a YouTube short on this show and
That's true
Yeah, so
But so the actually one of the fuzzy say one of the folks in the the YouTube chat says
So gods can create humans but not earplugs
Apparently yes the earplugs and not yet
I think it's Odysseus who figures that out
Who's another clever guy?
So they actually make several attempts at wiping out humanity.
And Aya, right?
Aya slash Inki, right?
Sort of keeps interfering with their plans.
Curse.
So, first they decide they're going to wipe out all the humans with a plague.
So they said a plague.
But then Aya goes and teaches the humans like medicine.
to cure the plague. They say, well, okay, we're not going to send any rain. So there'll
be a famine and they'll all die of hunger. Like these are really cool gods, huh? Like these
are the, yeah. I, or Christianity, everything was like cool and yeah, or loving, especially
loved women. Yeah. Yeah. So colonialism, I tell you. So they do that. But then A. comes
and teaches them far.
techniques and things and stuff and gets around the famine. Right. And so the other great guys are like,
thank you. Chris.
But so you can see in there this element of there being spirit, right, in this case,
Aya, this God, who's like giving this technology and stuff to man like to help them. Right.
Lala Prometheus, Lala the watchers, Lala, etc. Right. That kind of idea here.
And so finally, after those two things get foiled,
tip number three, they're like, okay, well, we're just going to send a flood.
We're just going to wipe everything out with a flood.
Yeah, right.
Get around that.
And so A goes to Ostra Haasus and tells him how to build a boat.
Yeah.
So he's kind of like a permeteous figure sort of, you know, giving this wisdom, you know,
right, right.
And so that's how he tries to get around it.
Now, obviously, that's not going to save everybody.
But at least potentially, right, can save otarosis and his family and a bunch of animals.
It's worth noting also that Enlil, not just because of his behavior here, is kind of the
devil.
Yeah, there's something in, was it Isaiah?
Yeah.
and Lil was the most I got at this point, right?
original Babylonian empire, right? Like the Bronze Age Babylonian empire. He was no longer
the most high god after the Bronze Age collapse. And of course, you have the ascendancy once the
Neo Babylonian empire starts, you have the ascendants of Marduk. So as we've talked about before on
the show when the fortune
of different cities and different empires and different political regimes, etc. on earth would rise
and fall. They saw everything on earth is like a mirror for everything that's going on in the
heavens. So that meant corresponding things were going on with the gods. And of course,
all of them had within their history built in the idea that whoever was the most high god at that
point wasn't always and might not be at some point in the future. Yeah, the succession myth.
Right, yeah, this is actually my-
that God had overthrown some other God to become the most high God and some other God could come along
overthrow him. This is what's going on in Isaiah, as we're talking about, Isaiah, when God says that
he's Yahweh and before him there was no one and after him there will be no other. Right? That's
pointing at the idea of no succession myth. Yeah. Yeah. Right. He is always and will always be
and the capital G God, God of God's right.
Most High God, eternally, right?
So Enlil has this fall, right, within their understanding.
And so when Isaiah, decides to talk about the fall of the devil,
the Hebrew there is, hello, Ben, Shakaar.
Okay, right? Should call...
is the name of the Morningstar aka Venus. This is the name that St. Jerome translated into Latin as
how art thou fallen Lucifer son of the morning. Yeah. Okay. But the hell out there is a Hebrew version.
There's good reason to believe. There's some good journal articles about this of NLIL.
So it's kind of a hebraization.
Right.
And this comes within a series of oracles against a Syria and Babylon.
Well, there you go.
Right.
And so in talking about the devil, it is both saying that they're devil worshipers.
And also, right, talking about the devil in terms of this fallen.
Yeah, you used to be something.
Now you're nothing.
Right.
So, N-Lil is kind of literally...
the devil. And Isaiah. And you can see why that connection would be made by his behavior here.
Right. He creates humanity as the slave race and then they get to be too many decides to wipe them out.
But does that remind you of anyone else you might have read about in the Hebrew Bible?
I don't know. Something in Exodus maybe? Yeah. Like Pharaoh.
Exodus chapter one.
Yeah, I mean, the whole complaint is they're multiplying.
There's too many, right?
Slaves are getting to be too many of them.
And what's his ultimate solution?
You see a male Hebrew baby, you drown it in the river.
Trown it in the river?
Yeah.
Flood.
Right.
So, that dynamic, right, that paradigm.
It's...
not just again some sort of Hebrew show Buddhism, our God's better than your God, right?
You know, your God's hateful and anti-human flourishing, right?
Note like the Babylonians themselves that their God was kind of hateful and anti-human flourishing.
Right? That's not a twist being put on their beliefs. That's their own story, right?
it is that they're most I got at least in this point kind of hates humans.
that's he is not a God who loves mankind like the God of the Bible. Yeah, which I mean,
we take that as so much as a given as Christians like, you know,
smile God loves you, but that is a crazy revolutionary thing to say within the context of ancient
paganism. Yes. No one was thinking what a friend we have in Zeus. You did not want Zeus to love you.
No bad things happen to you if Zeus gave the love.
view. That's right. Zeus goose first. Yes. Zeus goose on the loose. So that's sort of
the setup for the flood. And then we get to the tablet that Irving Finkel found. The
Finkel find is it were found as if by the fickle finger of fate. I'm sure. And that
actually that tablet is
incredibly interested in boat production.
Hmm. Pretty much the whole tablet is just about the details of the construction of this boat.
And probably the most interesting thing about the way this boat is described in this tablet
is that every other version of this, including the one in Genesis, the boat, the arc.
Right is rectangular, broadly rectangular.
Right. It is longer than it is wide and square. Right.
Whereas at this version, the boat is round.
So it is a kind of
Oracle boat that the Babylonians at the time used, I'll be at much larger
that was sort of like a big concave disk.
I'm sorry.
That would float up.
the water. And so in this tablet,
Autorhossus needs raw materials to build his boat so he tears down his house and
repurposes the wooden stuff. And it goes into great detail about how he created
ribs. The way you would reinforce the structure of the boat was there would be
sort of wooden ribs.
that ran the diameter of the circle,
right, going down into the concave portion, right,
at even angles, right,
like about every 10 degrees for 360 degrees, right?
And so those would reinforce sort of the whole structure.
And then there were, those bands would hold it together.
And so,
uh...
otterhossus then gets his family
And a bunch of animals on this giant circular disk.
And so when the flood happens, they're floating on this disk.
Right.
And so, you know, there's debate about the significance of the disk.
There are some people who take sort of the minimalist position, right?
that, um,
Basically, just East Target, that's the kind of boats Babylonians used.
Right? Like they, you know, so when he talks about building a boat, it's just a giant version of the boats they were familiar with.
Especially the level of detail. Right? They're like whoever, whoever did this version of the story, like, must have known a lot about boat construction.
Right, like probably lived a conjecture about what city he lived in based on where boats were made.
That kind of thing.
That's kind of the minimalist position.
Sort of the maximalist position would be that the disc represents their view of the dry land that makes up the world.
Right.
Which is sort of sitting on top of the waters so that the boat then is like a microcosm.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And the people who argue for that aren't just arguing based on that it's a disc, but that is a clear theme.
in Genesis, the idea of the ark is sort of a microcosm,
of the creation.
And so they say maybe that's an element shared with this story,
and that's related to the circular boat is a way of conveying that.
So then after the flood, right, the flood subsides,
and at our at our house,
this and his family are made immortal
after the flood.
But even though they're made immortal, the gods decide, hey, we can't let this happen
again with there being too many people.
And so Enlil and the other gods afflict humanity with early death, infant mortality, barrenness
to reduce the number of people going into the future.
which again is what a contrast.
with the Bible, you know, where God is always curing infertility. I shouldn't say always.
There are prominent stories of God making infertile women have babies and you know,
that the spirit is Adam and Eve, you know, be fruitful and multiply, you know.
Right, right. Yeah. And so yeah, so this is another air of complete contrast between the God of
of the Bible and the Babylonian gods.
Right.
God, the Old Man.
with babies. Super cool with babies. Yes. Right. He gives life. Right. He brings life out of death.
Right. He doesn't try to restrict life, minimize life. So then the thing you may have been thinking,
we were going to badly talk about here in this first half, but we're only getting to now
Now, the epic of yoga mess.
Yeah, this is the one where if people have the idea of, you know, that there are multiple
ancient flood stories and they're able to mention a second one, beyond Genesis. This is the
one that they've heard. They probably mention the Epic of Gilgamesh. Yeah.
Which is significantly the children of Thomas episode of Star Trek Next Generation.
Yes. Yes.
Darmine Dean.
Jalad.
That's an algorithm.
Yeah.
So I don't know if you what if you enjoyed that episode you really need to watch lower decks really I did love that that's one of my favorite episodes of because there's a guy there's a guy from that race who's a security officer on the ship.
So they actually made it.
Yes, wow.
I will have to check that out.
So the epic of Gilgamesh, like the epic of Atrahasis, right, obviously is not primarily about
the flood.
In fact, even less so in that Gilgamesh is not the guy who survives the flood, right?
It's not even the main character.
The guy who went through the flood is a supporting character in part of the epic of Gilgamesh, right?
So it is an epic that contains a flood story, right?
It is not itself a flood story per se.
But
Honestly, what is there of the flood story is almost identical to the Sumerian flood
story. To the point that Utnapishdom, who is the flood survivor in the epic of Gilgamesh,
in Akkadian basically means the same thing as Zia Sudra in Sumerian.
So this is what in technical terms we would call a KELK CAO Q.
the long lived one, well with a long life, right? And that is the primary role. Like we're told
about how he survived the flood. The flood thing is narrated sort of his backstory for who this
guy is. His importance in the epic of Gilgamesh isn't about him surviving the flood really. That sort
of secondary, it's that as the flood survivor, he has, he's immortal, like Autorhossus was made
immortal and so he has the secret.
the Entadiluvian secrets, including the secret of immortality.
And Gilgamesh, after the death of Enkidu, the rest of the epic of Gilgamesh
is all about him trying to avoid death.
Right?
And so he searches out, he pushed him and
he puts him through these trials to see if he's worthy of immortality.
and the trials are essential.
to see whether or not Gilgamesh's subject to human weaknesses.
So, I raised two-thirds God in one-third human.
Yeah, yeah.
Right. He's a giant.
So, it's, you know, can you go without sleeping?
Right. Can you go without eating or drinking?
Right, for these long periods of time.
And of course, he fails those trials.
And he tries to grab the flower that holds.
the secret of immortality, flowers, which of course turn into fruit.
How about that?
But it is snatched away by a serpent.
Yes.
And so...
Yeah, this is like, why you can see, this is one of the ones that some people say,
Oh, the Bible just plagiarizing Gilgamesh. Yeah. Yeah. Or, you know, sl-
elements of the biblical version of the story are found in Gilgamesh also.
No, no, no, no, no, could go.
But here again, like you, the Samaritan flood story,
Pish Tim is basically this guy who's really clever and knows these secret things,
and that's how he survived the flood, and that's how he became immortal.
Right? But that cleverness and stuff is connected again to his relationship
with Aya, with Enki, with the same God.
right. So it really...
The flood story part was really falls in with what we've already been talking about.
So then finally, our last sort of, the last witness to ancient near eastern
Mesopotamian paganism is a fellow by the name of Barosis and I know we've brought him up a couple
of times at least in brief on the show before. Barosis is his actual name. Barosis is the Greek version
again.
of his name, which was actually Belire Ushu.
Also a difficult one to name your child?
Yes.
Well, I would not recommend naming your child that,
because it needs bail is his shepherd.
Yeah, yeah, that doesn't go over well.
Yeah.
And so what happened is by the time you get to the Greek period,
he's right, he's living in the third century BC.
OK, so the 200s BC.
So he's living under the Greeks.
Bye.
So let me go to the cell eukits. And so with the rise of the Greeks and everything,
what has happened is, in that they have survived it all, and not been sort of absorbed into
Greek religious traditions, the Mesopotamian traditions have all kind of assimilated to each other.
So in the neo-Babalonean Empire, Marduk is the role of most high
God. So we're talking about their deobabalone empire. We're talking about like the sixth century BC.
And then over time, as you get into the Persian period and this assimilation starts happening,
Martin gets assimilated with Bale. First Bale comes into Babylonian religion as Bale,
B-E-L. So think about the story, the additional piece of Daniel that's found in the Greek version,
Bell in the Dragon.
right? Yeah. He's in Babylon. And then gets assimilated to Marduk. So by the time you're in the
third century BC, our friend Barosis is a priest at the Temple of Bell Marduk. Like they just
hyphenate it. Like yeah, Bell Marduk, basically the same guy, right? So they've taken the sort of
Syrian Semitic pagan traditions and the Babylonian Mesopotamian pagan religious traditions are just kind
of.
put it all together in so far as it has survived it all, right, into the Greek era.
But so that makes Borosus sort of the repository of all of this tradition.
And he then writes in Greek.
And he writes about these traditions, two Greeks in Greek, as a way of both preserving these
traditions and showing points of continuity and interest as it relates to.
Greek pagan religion. And the main text he wrote, which does not still exist by the way,
we don't actually have his text, we just have lengthy quotes from it.
Okay. Yeah. And we have quotes from it from all kinds of people. Yeah. Which doesn't
say, I mean, there is a whole, I don't know, is there must be a technical term for this,
there's a whole category of literature from the ancient world that we only know through
quotes
Yeah, authors, yeah, recitations. Yeah. Yeah. And because of that, you always have to be again,
you always have to be a little careful. Right. Because when we only know them from quotes,
number one, we don't have any context for those quotes. Yep. So you're just kind of assuming that
the person quoting them is doing it accurately to the context, right? And doesn't have an agenda
of their own, you know?
You know, I assume that this is the biggest place where this is a problem.
Okay, when you're reading theological stuff, especially if you're reading early
petristics, is you will see people referring to papias all the time.
Well papias said xyz, papias taught papias in his work, thus and so said.
Yeah, we don't have any of papias's works.
They didn't survive.
We only have papers in quotes.
Hmm. And some of those quotes are for people like you,
CBS of Cessaria, who sometimes have somewhat suspect motives.
You notice you see,
be a success area is not sent you,
CBS of Cessaria.
No, because he was an Aryan, a turtuncle.
So you have to be a little careful, right?
When you see somebody just quoting papias, right?
Really, you should always quote it at papias as quoted by
Yeah, yeah, right this person said right and you see this is the only person who quotes him right but by saying as quoted by you
At least know where to look to see this quote you can at least see the context you at least see what the author was doing with the quote
You could assess some things right yeah, so but he's got this text called the
I'm not even sure how pronounced is well in Greek would it be something like Vavilloniaca or something
Yeah, something like that which is Greek for Babylonian things.
Yeah, it's kind of like, I mean, it's just Babylonian things.
Yeah, it's just Babylonian things.
It's like similar to our word Americana.
Yeah.
Although we mean something particular by that, but yeah.
Babylonian stuff.
But so we don't have it, but he gets, we have quotes and he gets quoted by all at length
by all kinds of people.
He gets quoted by Greek and Roman pagans.
He gets quoted in some Jewish sources.
He gets quoted by church fathers and Christian sources.
Right, when they're talking about...
like the pagan religions of Mesopotamia.
He's sort of their go-to because he wrote in Greek,
so they can read it.
Most of those people did not know any
subnitical languages, let alone any kind of Babylonian.
That's of any age.
He compiles all of these Mesopotamian traditions
as they had survived to that point in Greek.
And that includes we have quoted in two different-
places at some link by Greek pagan authors, his version of the flood story. And so his
version, the hero is in Greek Zissuthros, or Zissuthros, which you could kind of see Zia
the sudra in there, right? Yeah. Yeah. Which is the the Sumerian name, right? And he is the
son of Othirtis, right?
Remember Ubar Tutu?
So those seem to have been preserved.
He just kind of hellenizes them
because he's writing in Greek
and he got a hellenized names.
And in his retelling, the sudra has this dream
in its chronos who comes to warn him about the flood.
So, A here or Enki has been...
And for at least for barosis's purposes to the audience he's talking to is seen as being
equivalent with chronos, right?
Which kind of fits because this would be an older tier of gods, not the current tier of
gods with Marduk.
It's the previous administration as it were.
And so, Zia Sudra, then in this version,
a story builds a boat for himself and his close personal friends and a bunch of animals.
Hey, so this is the only Babylonian flood hero who actually cares about his friends.
He's the only one who's a good friend.
The other ones like immediate family, cool, everybody else, forget it.
Not good for genetic diversity, you guys.
Yes, but he brings his friends with him.
interesting detail that gets added here.
that isn't in the others.
Is Barosis says that before the flood happens,
the Suthoros goes and goes to Nippur, interestingly,
Nippur being the city where the tablet we have
of the Sumerian flood story came from.
And he buries sort of all of the wisdom, all of the
Anteludoluvian pre-Flood wisdom in history,
berries all the tablets there at Nippur.
And that's why the Babylonians of Anteluvian wisdom.
And so this is remember, we've talked about before,
the original Babylonian empire, they claimed,
homerabi at all, the Amuru, the Amurites,
claimed to have the wisdom from before the flood.
This version of story, Burosis explained how that
explains how that worked, right?
They buried it on tablets, right?
and clay tablets would survive a flood,
especially if you buried them underground.
Some other details here,
Borosis has, at the end of the flood,
the Suthoros starts releasing birds,
to go look for dry land.
Huh.
These birds are unidentified as just species.
Right.
Yeah.
But just birds.
And when they finally don't come back.
He says, oh, they found dry land, right?
Also immediately when they disembark
And by the way the boat in this one again like we said
Only the otter has this one is round this one is also right a big rectangle
But the boat when it lands the flood water subsides they immediately come out and offer sacrifices to the gods and
then
The soothros is told that as a reward
reward for being...
so wise and so clever to rob you the flood, he gets to become a God.
Hey, and so he sort of gives his part in a dress to his friends and families.
It's he's going off to become a God and live with the gods and tells them,
hey, by the way, guys, here's where I buried the tablets.
Here's the treasure map. Go find those.
You'll have all of the wisdom and knowledge.
And interestingly, so this to be is the most interesting part.
Barosis after telling this story.
which is we've seen is very much in keeping. He's preserved all the way down to the third
century BC the basic structure of these traditions going back more than a thousand years, right?
In these stories. But Barossa says, part of the boat still exists in Armenia and you can go see it.
Wow. And he says, not only can you go see it, this part of the boat, but the pitch,
Right? That they used to seal the boat.
Seal the one boat.
People go and...
Grape the pitch off and use it in spellcasting.
Wow.
It is magic tar.
Amazing.
Babylonian bitch says it where.
And you could go on pilgrimage
to this chunk of boat in our media
and get the magic tar according to Blerosis.
I don't know how, I mean who knows?
We'll never know how true that was, right?
If that was just a
or if there was some enterprise at young fellow with a big chunk of old wood,
it was selling magic tar. I mean, you know,
very well.
I've been. Yeah. Yeah.
All right, with all those ancient tales told, you've wasted another perfectly good hour and
16 minutes of your life listening to this first half of Lord's Spirit's podcast. We would
take short break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven
young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
For centuries.
The Byzantine music has sustained Orthodox worship around the world.
Now, the St. John Cooquoiselli's Institute of the Trigical Arts offers online classes
in notation, theory, and practice, and free classes in liturgics with a faculty led by
John Michael Boyer, author of the acclaimed book Byzantine Champ to the Received Tradition.
Registration is open now for classes in September at Cooquoiselli.net.
That's k-o-u-k-o-u-z-e-l-i-s.net.
We're back in-
Now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
Apparently this show is now so popular, I have to read a second ad.
Can you believe it, Father Stephen?
Capitalism just taking over the program.
That's right.
Just at a merch shop too.
Oh
It's true. I'm expecting to just show up at the conference and there's going to be like
patches with like Pepsi logos and stuff all over your casak.
You're not doing that? You're going to look like an Asgard driver.
So yes, this episode is also sponsored by the Orthodox Studies Institute at St.
Constee College by Poppeter Demand. OSI is partnering with the symbolic world to offer
course on Jubilee's and the Nephilim.
by you, Father Stephen D. Young, who be? Yes, you. In this course, Father Stephen will guide students
through the Book of Jubilee's expansion of biblical history, unveiling the significance of the
fall of the angels, the rise of the Nephilim and the heavenly origins of the Feast of the Old
and New Testaments. Along the way, he'll explore how Jubilee's reinterpreted creation,
demonology, and the prophetic structure of time, and why these themes matter not only to second
can't tell the Judaism but to later Christian understand
the unseen world. Live classes are held on Tuesday, seven to nine PM central time through September 23rd. So you can register now to catch up on the first four sessions and join the remaining two sessions live. Go to www.TheSymbolicWorld.com
slash courses to sign up.
Yeah, the actual.
I'm actually technically.
Oh, uh, next.
Tuesday is actually the last class proper.
Oh, what's that?
We're gonna finish up the book of Jubilee's.
The week after that on September 23rd,
if you are registered, you get to sit in
on a conversation between me and Peugeot.
What?
About all the stuff I've been saying.
I mean, you've already replaced me with a dog
throughout the class, up to that point.
And then here's the cool part,
I've been baiting him all along the way.
Oh man.
Like in what episode?
or in what episode in one in one lesson right one of the class periods
I said I'm not worried about AI and explain to why like I am
I have laid the groundwork and setting traps. I've never seen that you triggered in big time with that one so September 23rd
It's gonna all go down
Nice live on zoom and you can be there wow, that's not actually on zoom. It's on the symbolic world platform
But you can be there live on a zoom and you could ask questions. You can stir the pot
Yeah, further beyond what I've already stirred it. Speaking of pot stirring, we're going to take
a couple questions. You okay with that, Father? I think so. We have someone who has been waiting
a very long time now, actually. We have James calling from Denver. James, welcome to Lord
Spirit's podcast. Good evening, Father. Sorry about James. Thank God. How are you? Take this slowly.
I know the air is thin.
It really is. I grew up with asthma and it's challenging living out here. Oh, man. Maybe
you should move, James. Just throwing that out there. Well, it's God has a wonderful
creation out here and I wouldn't be able to move. All right. I mean, come down here to
Southern Louisiana. It's so humid. The air is actually thick. Yeah. You actually have
to see the exact opposite.
I'll know so you can chew on it.
Yeah.
So what is up there from the mile high city?
So I had a specific question.
According to modern Old Testament scholarship, there is the narrative that there is the J source,
which is the Yahweh source and the T source, the Priestly source.
No, man, they were essentially woven together to form one cohesive story.
For example, if we look at Genesis 6 and 7, we find the distinction of how they
animals are to be numbered and brought into the ark. We like to genesis seven and eight. We find different
durations of the flood things about nature. Is there any merit to this theory or do we
as Orthodox Christians reject this theory? All right. Come on. Let's hear the rant, Father. No
and yes. All right, good night. So yeah, I mean you even left some of the sources out.
It's that that theory people know of is J E D P right it's actually called the documentary hypothesis
uh goes back to well it goes way back but the sort of classical four of it is in Klaus Wellhausen
German name you might note and so you've got J that's the Yahweh Yahweh's source
you've got
E which is the Elohist source, D which is just the book of Deuteronomy, and P which is
the post-exilic priestly source. And this went through phases, right? So it started out,
it was just sort of a J and E thing because people noticed, hey, and some of these passages
particularly in Genesis but also in the rest of the Torah.
There's some place.
where God is called Yahweh, there are some places where he's called Elohim, right?
And so, originally, originally, if you go all the way back, the first guy to have this theory
in the 18th century was actually trying to defend Mosaic authorship by identifying the sources
that Moses used.
So his idea was that Moses used preexisting sources, and Moses is the one who brought them
together.
And what God was called was part of the basis for making that division.
And then various theories, I could go on and on, but that's various theories about
Deuteronomy being different. And you could, textually, Deuteronomy is stylistically and stuff a
little different than the other four books. So it's not based on nothing. It's a question of whether
that basis is enough.
to support the theory that they then built.
And then the whole idea of P,
of there being this post-exilic priestly source,
is based on the presupposition that
Israelite religion had to evolve.
That it had to start in one place, basically polytheistic
de-regure paganism.
And then it became some kind of vaguely
monotheistic thing that resembled the religion of the Bible only after the exile.
And so anything that sounds like that kind of religion can't possibly have existed in
the time of Moses or even before the exile and therefore all of that stuff had to be added
by priests who edited the text after the exile.
And it is a beautiful piece of circular reasoning.
Right, because...
Well, all of this and that, right, like the distinction between, we're talking about the flood story tonight,
the distinction between clean and unclean animals. That is the making sense at Genesis. That's before Leviticus.
So that must have been added by the priests after the exile, right? And he said, well, how do you know it was added by priests after the exile?
the exile and the answer is well because that's stuff that priests would add after the exile.
That didn't exist before the exile.
Well, how do you know it didn't exist before the exile?
Because it only gets added by the priest after the exile.
So it's just this kind of circular thing, right?
And the whole distinction between J and E sort of assumes that one author
couldn't refer to God by multiple names.
Yeah.
And part of the part of the problem with that is
There are actually other names.
used for God like L.O. and in El Shaddai in the Torah, they don't hypothesize those as being separate
sources. For some reason, like they acknowledge, I mean, you look at any, let's just talk about pagan
religions, the ancient Ereas, they all had piles of different titles for their gods. Any given
god has a pile of titles, right? Why couldn't, why couldn't ancient Israel have had the same thing,
right? So there's just, there's not actually evidence to support it. You have to approach it with
with priest.
positions, but so it reached a point where it went crazy. You could pick up stuff from the early 20th
century where you have people writing again with total confidence. Total confidence talking about
this half of this verse comes from J2. Because they'd have like J123 and 4 as separate sources. Wow.
and E12345, right? P1 and 2, right?
They just write with total got this half of the I mean two words out of a verse would come from one source and the other two words would come from another source and you're like
what right
um
And as you point out right so you point out some duplications
This is this is another problem with this theory so we're to assume that the final editor was both brilliant at bringing all these texts together and a complete idiot because he didn't notice all the places where he left seems
Like that.
Like why would he leave a re duplication?
Why wouldn't he have corrected that if there was one guy who was putting this all together, the final editor?
Right, it sort of doesn't make sense.
But that, a lot of that theory, that sort of super elaborate form of that theory, they even did a, they did a critical addition of J at one point too.
of a not-existent text.
Um, but that theory has largely fallen out of favor now, at least in the super elaborate
form. The J in the E part is mostly out of favor. Um, still your average secular old testament
scholar thinks due to our enemy is by a completely different author and from a late date.
uh... there are reasons
that i won't go into it as long argument
Why I don't think that's the case.
A good part of that argument is in Meredith Cline's Treaty of the Great King.
The...
So but that's most people think.
And most people think that sort of the final layer of editing on the Torah as a whole, right?
And we've talked before on the show about there's definitely editing between what Moses wrote and what we now have.
in terms of updating the language, updating place names, all that kind of stuff.
Most certainly the last stage of that editing was probably done by priests because they were the
ones who were literate and who had possession of the texts. Right? Sometime in the time of Ezra,
there's good reason to believe that. A different second-tumble traditions and stuff.
So, everybody kind of believes that in various forms of it.
You know.
But...
Mostly now people have a more it's less based on like
discrete words and parts of verses and sentences come from different texts that existed and more of
This is a body of texts that developed over time and they and different scholars will chart that development in different ways
They'll have it's more now that different parts of it are older or newer
right
Rapp.
and like deuteronomy the whole thing being newer and that kind of thing rather than chopping everything up into tiny pieces
Because you kind of get a big house of cards and then it all falls down
with that approach yeah
So yeah, there's there's no
To me the biggest thing though in terms of the second part of your question of whether orthodox people should pay any attention to it is
It's not actually at all helpful
Thank you.
Right, I mean, if you're trying to publish a journal article arguing for the existence of J7,
okay, right, gives you something to write a journal article about.
But I mean, in terms of what the text of Genesis means, what it's saying to you,
how it's been interpreted and applied by the church over the centuries,
all that theorizing and stuff is irrelevant.
Yep.
So, you know, I mean if you're a nerd and you want to get into it.
you know, go do a PhD in Old Testament. Cool, more power to you. Right, but in
terms of regular Orthodox Christians, it's it's really kind of useless. And
Well-housing basically said that at the end of his life.
Hmm.
Alrighty. Well, thanks very much for calling, James.
Alright, well we're going to take one more call before we roll on with our story.
of great inundations. We have Caleb calling from Monare and California, so Caleb, welcome
Lord of Spheres podcast.
Hey, thank you so much, Jeremy.
Yeah, we hear you. What up, dog?
All right. Well, this show has changed my life, so thank you both for your work. Before
my real question, I have to ask this after five years, I don't think I have to imagine
somebody else is thorn in this. So does this show have three hands as a reference to the next
We Mitchell and if so, does this make the show two thirds divine.
Wow.
Who's the other third, I ask you, is it Mike don't tell Ken Ham to
again? Or can he even straight out every so often.
Yeah, I don't know if we should reveal the origin of the three
halves people who know, no.
Yeah, that's one of those.
If you know you know, things if you know, you know, yeah, I'm
just going to put that out there.
You don't have to be from the state of Massachusetts.
but it helps. True. Well, my real question is a little more on topic, but I'm going to
read this so I get it right. In Matthew 24, Jesus says that at the time of his second coming,
the world will be like the days of Noah, Mary, and Gives him a marriage. Who would that be
a reference to the method of spiritual returning in the end times and connect with some ideas
about the Capitol A anti-Christ being fully demonized.
particularly wildly, a lot of messianic sounding transhumanists and UFO cultists
hope for a literal biological merger with either super AI or quote unquote aliens,
which could lead through the very rituals that were talking about happening in modern times.
Wow. Well, I guess I did start out by making coast to coast AM references at the beginning.
I mean, yes, obviously I will pass this to you.
Father Steven, just because I want to hear what you have to say. But I mean, they'll be marrying and
giving in marriage as in the days of Noah. That doesn't like, like, the Nephilim ritual wasn't what
most of marriage in the days of Noah was about. That was, you know, the certain God kings doing
that kind of stuff, whatever. But so yeah, I think it's, I don't know, maybe I'm wrong, but my
sense of that is that it's really about like.
people are just not even going to see it coming.
You know, there's going to be going about life as they normally would, making plans for
the future, you know, getting married, having kids, et cetera, et cetera.
So I take it in a much more kind of humdrum mundane way.
I don't know.
What do you think, father?
Is that a reference to that or?
I hate to poop on your party.
Oh, go for it.
Unmind your stick in your proverbial mud.
No, our call.
Okay.
Yeah.
But so what the text actually says in Matthew 2438
is for as in those days before the flood,
they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage
until the day when Noah entered the ark.
And if you look at the broader context, this is talking about nobody knowing
Yeah, when, when the return of
or the glorious appearing of Christ is going to happen.
The idea being, right, it's not like the everybody other than Noah, of course,
who had been tipped off saw the flood coming, right?
Being there were just going about their business, eating and drinking, getting married,
starting businesses, right?
Doing all these things as if, you know, they had a future that was going to go on forever
and then suddenly boom, that's it, it's over.
Right. That's that's kind of what the Matthew text is aimed at. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. It's not that weird. Although stuff you were talking about is way cooler. So that's why I'm sorry. I had to put my stick in your mud.
But well, I mean he is from California, so
You know his land of fruits and nuts so you can I go ahead and mowed slides. Yeah, and much. Yeah, exactly. Oh God bless him. Yeah
Yeah, thanks for calling Caleb.
All right, well, we're gonna rule.
The Caleb means dog in Hebrew.
Oh, wow.
You see what I did there?
Wow.
See, I didn't know that actually.
I feel like I should have.
I am a man of little Greek, less Latin and even less Hebrew
to paraphrase Ben Johnson.
As is your what?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what about the big funds?
story, the other big flood story everybody's heard of, you know, the not the Gilgamesh one,
but the other one.
Everyone's favorite hotel in casino.
Atlantis.
Yes.
How many times have you been there?
Zero.
Oh, zero.
Okay.
You just know about it.
Everybody knows about it.
Come on, man.
Yes.
Yes, and this is this is we're we're talking about our world at land.
not cool Atlantis's with Namor or Aquaman or something. Cool comic book Atlantis's.
So, and this by the way, just to tip people off, this half of the show is part of our gift to you.
We're going to start out with Play-Doh. Things are going to get weird.
We're talking about some cool folks.
that even father Andrew didn't know about and I'm kind of surprised.
That's true. That's true. You do not listen to enough coast to coast clearly.
Yeah, or or any of it.
Arpelle, George, Norrie, they all have things to teach you my friend.
But yeah, I mean, the thing it was funny to me.
I think most people, if they think about Play-Doh, now we've referenced, and actually in one of our
maybe first or second episode, I think,
We referenced some of this stuff.
But when most people think about Plato, they think about philosophical dialogues and so forth.
And they probably do not realize, I feel like this is a meme or something, you know, that
guy who's dancing alone in the corner in the party or something like, you know, they don't
know that Plato is actually his source of our Atlantis stories.
Yes, pretty much our only source.
Yeah, like it's funny.
The only exit source.
Everybody else who talks about it is...
talking about it by way of Plato. Right. And I think that, I mean,
Atlantis is such, it's such a kind of a cultural meme, like for a long time, a long, long,
long time, that the origin point of that story, of that version of the flood story, I think is
almost completely lost for most people. If you're to ask him, like, where did we get the
Lennon's story from.
Most people definitely not mention Plato.
Yeah.
Yeah, no, as the source, no.
It's got to be assumed that there is some Greek and or Roman myth.
Yeah. Yeah. Like, you know, if they know, if they could name some sources of Greek and or Roman myth, they might say,
was it an eziut or something? You know, you know, which yeah, yeah.
Although as I pointed out for Father Andrew, the greatest source for knowledge of the story of the thinking of Atlantis is
is
the incredible animatronic fountain display at Caesar's Palace in Las Vegas.
You could find this on the YouTube's kids.
Rival only by the Calabeth in the summer and it is animatronic, vaguely creepy characters
that rise up out of a fountain. There are fire effects. I've seen it in person,
but video is the next best thing.
Yeah.
So anything with animatronics underutilized, I feel, except at Disneyland.
There are perhaps overutilized.
So yes, Plato talks about Atlantis in two of his dialogues, the Tameis and the Critias.
If you don't know a lot about Plato, Plato's dot-
dialogues are named after the main interlocutor, the person who Socrates is talking to in the dialogue.
Yeah. So the Tameis is mainly, there are some other people, but the main people talking in it are
Plato, or not Plato, sorry, Socrates and Tameis. And then the critis, the main people talking are Socrates and Critis.
And so this is our old
a source like we mentioned
everybody else who talks about
it in the ancient world
including like
fathers and stuff who refer to Atlantis are all referring to Plato when they're
referred to it. That said, Plato claims he's getting it from somewhere else. Right? We just
don't have any citations of that other person except for Plato's. Everybody else is
exciting Plato. So in the Tameas, so Plato's Tameas is essentially Plato's version of the
creation story.
which I became intimately familiar with when I translated it in a Greek independent study I did in my undergrad.
And you know when I figured out that was a bad idea?
I figured out that was a bad idea when I spent three days working on this chunk of it
and then finally sort of gave up and went and found a translation.
And in the translation it said, this section is hopelessly corrupt.
And I was like cool
don't even um
So
But the Tobias is sort of his creation story. That's where he talks about the Demi urge
Right
Which is sort of like Aristotle's world soul although distinct in several ways the Demi urge crafts everything according to the interplay of chance and necessity
et cetera, et cetera, right
Interestingly, interesting.
interestingly, in the Naghamadi Library, the big find of ancient
Gnostic texts, there was a copy of Plato's to Mass, in there with the things like the Gospel
of Mary Magdalene and all of these things, Gospel wisdom.
So it seems to have held on to been the Nostek creation, part of the Nostek creation.
at least at some level.
But so Atlantis has talked about
there briefly in terms of the creation story,
the main place where Plato talks about
the Atlantis story and Atlantis as such
is the critis.
And in the critis, it's really talking about
the history of the world,
especially the history of the world, Vizavipolitics.
So...
while it's unclear in the critis, so the critis talks about where Atlantis was in relationship
to the pillars of Hercules, which are the ancient name for what we call the Strait of
Gibraltar, which is sort of the gateway from the Mediterranean to the Atlantic Ocean.
The Atlantic Ocean, by the way, takes its name from Atlantis.
But
It's the ocean where Atlantis was. That's where it gets its name.
And so based on that, you might conjecture that, well,
and this is true, pretty much every later interpreter understands Atlantis to have been
outside the Mediterranean on the other side of the Straits of Gibraltar. But in the
critis itself, that's not totally clear. Whether it was a big island in the Mediterranean or whether it
that was on the other side.
But everyone later on, it's the other side.
Um.
And not only was there this big island, right, this gigantic island where the Atlantean
civilization proper was, but they had gone out from there and conquered most of the Mediterranean
Basin. So they had conquered Europe basically over toward Greece and they had conquered
North or there in Africa right up to the border of Egypt.
Again, according to critics in the critics.
Now, supposedly Plato says of the critics, he is getting this information about Atlantis
from Egyptian historical records, which he claims were translated by Solon.
So long, famously, took a trip from Athens.
to Egypt at the beginning of the sixth century. So we're talking about 590 BC.
So Plato's in the fourth century. So we're about 250 years before Plato.
Right, 200, 250 years before Plato.
Plato says, so long when he went there and he translated the Egyptian historical records,
he found all this stuff about Atlantis and their records.
Again, we have no
So other record of this Solon stuff about Atlantis.
And this is kind of a stereotype way.
Whenever you read a Greek author, a classical Greek author who claims they have some esoteric
knowledge of ancient things, they always claim they got it by way of Egypt.
Yeah, that's where all the old stuff comes from.
Yes, Egypt is all the old stuff.
is the oldest civilization they knew of, they kind of...
thought it was the first civilization on Earth. They traced everything back there.
Right. So they're the old civilization. They must know all this old stuff. And whatever
they do is the old way of doing it. Right. So his appeal to Solon, his Egypt is kind of stereotypical.
Right. But so what we are told is that when, and we've talked about this before,
the
talks about this in the Critias and other places. But in the Critias, this about Atlantis comes after the part that we've quoted several times on this show, where Plato talks about during the age of Kronos, Kronos having divvied up the sort of land and nations of the world among the gods.
Yes.
And this big island of Atlantis was given to Poseidon as his allotment.
And Poseidon
fell in love with a human woman, go figure. What Greek God ever did that?
Named Claydo. They say which one didn't. And Poseidon went to this human woman.
The sounding familiar at all. And made ten babies. Yeah, although, you know,
Two at a time. Yeah, five sets of twins. All dudes.
and Atlas, who was the eldest, was the first king of Atlantis and sort of the founder,
right, of Atlantian civilization, Atlantis getting its name from him.
He was Atlantis and it was Atlantis.
So he would sort of be the founder figure so
What this is setting up for the Greek pagan mind is that Poseidon would have been the God that they worshipped and
There would be a big temple to Poseidon
in the Acropolis the main city of Atlantis and then there would be the grave of atlas
Right attached to it as the shrine as we've talked about before in the way Greek temples were set
as the hero right
As the great man of old the nephilim as it were
I'm not sure.
What's this?
So, if you're for Nephilim, is it Nephilim?
Nope.
Just here, people say one of the Nephilim.
Yeah, technically it would be Nephilim.
But it's one of those things that never kind of occurs in the singular.
Mm.
Yeah.
They're never used in the singular.
They say one of the, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
One of the group, yeah.
I mean, if it's Greek, you've got gigas.
That's much easier.
Yeah.
So Atlantis then is structured.
the way the island like structured like the buildings and everything is in a series of concentric circles.
And that starts with a series of motes, like defensive motes around the island.
And then works its way inward up to, you know, the peak, the acropolis, right,
where the palace is and the temple of Poseidon and everything, right.
And so according to Plato and the
9,000 years ago from their perspective. So 9380 BC, right, give or take. The
Athenians go figure, decided to stand up to these evil slavour Atlanteans and
and drive them back.
And in the ensuing war,
the
ensuing war, the Atlantic armies get wiped out by a flood and Atlantis sinks into the sea.
But some of the members of the Atlantic and Royal family
who have some of that royal blood descended from Poseidon didn't get killed in the sinking
and they survived in various parts around the Mediterranean.
basin, and they then became sort of the kings, right? And the ruling class of all of the
early civilizations in the Mediterranean basin.
Yeah. They go on to, you know, found Gondor and Arnor and, you know, that kind of stuff.
Now if you want to talk plagiarism, I know Plato was in the public domain. I know he was
the public domain. The column of story.
which is brew my friend. You know I think my favorite part about Tolkien's
bit about the culture of story, which is in on fairy stories, is where he talks
about how Arthur, who is probably some historical figure, like stood in there
for centuries and then emerged as the Arthur of legend, you know, this sort of
weird anyway it's got a funny image to me the witch is prune
So this kind of raises the question though.
And this isn't just a modern question, interestingly.
This is going to sound like a modern question,
but it's actually not.
The question is Plato really reporting anything
that he thinks is historical?
Like is he being legit when he says he got this via
a soul on from Egyptian records, right?
Is he being legit when he talks about,
he thinks this is a civilization that actually existed?
or
is this just Atlantis, just this civilization that he's come up with rhetorically.
Yeah, some kind of figure that he's a rhetorical device because what he does in the
critis is he compares and contrast Atlantis with Athens to make Athens sort of the ideal
civilization by using the Atlantians as this bad example to contrast it.
Who could have seen that one coming right?
There's a good Athenian patriot, right?
So, I mean, Socrates chose to die rather than leave Athens, right?
Like, yeah, right.
So, right, so kind of which isn't, right?
And you may say, well, that's a really modern question.
It's really not because ancient people weighed in on it.
And when I say ancient people weighed in on it, I mean, the first person to say that it
was just an allegory and not actual history that Plato was
talking about was Aristotle, like his immediate student. Yeah. And he said, oh, well, Aristotle
would have known, right? So it must, it must just be an allegory, right? But here's the thing.
There's this other fella, Cran Tor, who was the student of another one of Plato's students.
So sort of a philosophical grandson of Plato who said no it was absolutely real.
and Plato like meant this to be history. So that disagreement goes back almost to
Plato's lifetime as to what he meant whether he thought it was real or not. My answer
to this question is, is what might expect for our anniversary episode.
Porky Noodles.
Here we go.
Fan service everywhere in this episode.
That...
Plato did think there was an actual Atlantis,
in ancient times that was destroyed, the broad strokes.
But then a lot of the details,
and of the way he's telling the story,
and portraying Atlantis is designed
within the critics to represent this contrast with Athens
and make certain points about Athenian,
the Athenian way of life.
Both can be true.
Right. You could be using, you know, something that they can...
considered to be they thought was basically historical but then elaborating it in a way to make a philosophical point.
Yeah. Um, so then Atlantis then gets picked up by
for people of interest to people uh, listening to the to this show by Filo of Alexandria.
Yeah, I'm telling you a writer it's fan service left
in right in this episode. And a whole bunch of early Christian sources,
Ed Churchfathers. Yeah, who all Christian source would be like
Turtullian. Yeah, churchfather would be like Clement.
Say Clem, there you go. Turtullian is another church uncle.
Yeah, we talk about Atlantis. Yeah, they, and they all kind of treat it like
this is totally real. Real thing. It was in the Atlantic Ocean.
Right. Yeah. As everything. And they even, they even say,
That's why you can't navigate the Atlantic Ocean.
Yeah, because Atlantis is down there cursing the place if you try and head west, right?
You got sunken Atlantis down there and there's eddies and currents and stuff and your boat will get wrecked and never come back
And what does that say about America? I ask you yeah, oh
We'll get there soon. I know
We'll get there soon. This is the Harbour gets really weird. We're about to get weird. I know
So this is gonna be so good you guys, you're gonna love it.
But before that, we're gonna segue it.
that maybe. The other thing you get, interestingly, especially in some of the early Christian sources,
is they will assert that Plato's story of Atlantis is borrowed from Moses.
Yeah, because Moses has to be the oldest possible source of everything.
So yeah, right. And specifically the flood story. So they're making a connection with the flood story.
Right. Amazing. And you may think, oh, well, okay. Ancient civilization destroyed
See?
Flood, right? Giants, sons of gods. That's not the sort of connection they draw though. Right?
Are you ready for the number one piece of evidence they use to say, hey, this is plagiarized from Moses? I am ready.
Poseidon had ten sons, right? Yeah, ten sons who are kings. Yeah. How many generations are there
from Adam to the Flood.
Oh, 10.
See, that proves it right there, right?
Obvious.
But I mean, of course, I mean, so obvious.
It seems a little crazy to us, but that just sort of underlines the way that, like, numbers
functioned as story elements.
The way they were reading those genealogies.
Yeah.
They weren't reading them as, like, literal numbers and literal generation.
They saw all these numbers as being significant beyond that.
Yeah.
Right.
As saying these other things, right.
So then the rest of this half we're going to be answering the question, how did Atlantis
get weird?
Because you notice I didn't say anything about crystals or new age or occultism or weird
racial science.
time.
think about Plato. I mean, there's definitely some whack of
doodle stuff in Plato, but yet all of that stuff is associated
with lettuce. We're about to tell you how that happened.
Yes. Buckle up.
Folk how it land has got out of hand.
And it all starts. It all starts when Europeans discovered
quote unquote, the new world.
Because think about it. Think about it for a second here. In
you are, try to put yourself.
for a second into the frame of mind of an old world,
European or whatever.
And you think of Atlantis as being out there
in that unnavigable Atlantic ocean.
And somebody manages to cross it.
And then finally, something.
Yeah, it said word back.
So you have one hook in your brain for land mass
out in the Atlantic ocean.
Well, not just that.
But once they get there, they...
tell you because remember my in civilization is already ceased to exist. Yeah. By the time
Europeans get there, they find all these ancient ruins, advanced empire with stuff like pyramids,
and all this stuff. And they're like, well, who are these people? Where do these people come from?
You guys. Where do these ruins come from? Who built them?
Clearly, right, there used to be a continent.
in the middle of that ocean. And so when it sank, the survivors went in both directions.
So the Mayans, the Aztecs, these are all descended from it, the Indian civilization, just
like all the folks of the Mediterranean basin, right? That's why they all got pyramids and
stuff. It's not just that, you know, stacking rocks in a pyramid shape, they tend to stand
up longer that if you stack them in.
other ways. No, right? This is all connected to one root culture, the Atlantian culture.
Atlantis proven by the existence of people in North and South America.
Amazing. And this influence is, you could find it in Thomas Morris, Utopia, you could find some of
the influence of this, of the idea of Atlantis being out there. I have to say, as someone who did
it is undergrad doing run-
in the science, English literature.
Utopia is one of those texts
that a lot of people have heard the name of
and have some idea of,
probably don't know that it's a text.
In most cases.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And really read it, you guys.
You should totally read it.
It's a really wild, crazy satirical piece of writing.
If you've read Thomas Moore,
it's one of those texts that if you've read it
and you hear someone talking about it,
you can instantly tell whether they've actually read it or not.
Yes, this is
This is one of the original things.
Like Nietzsche.
Like if you've actually read Nietzsche and you're talking about Nietzsche, you can instantly
tell whether they've actually read it or not.
Yeah.
So, yeah, it's one of those things.
But so, this is all that's influence, right?
And that's this vague idea of the origin of the minds and stuff.
Who is it who pulls this all together into a comprehensive theory?
A man named Ignatius Donnelly.
Which that's a great name.
Yes.
What did you think?
Who is your figure in American?
And a Congressman, right?
Was it a Congressman?
Yes.
For Minnesota.
Oh, oh.
With an Irish name.
The state wasn't one of your people from Minnesota.
There aren't a lot of Dutch in Minnesota.
That's Germanic people's.
Yeah.
Oh, we're getting there.
That's he wrote a book.
He had a, shall we say diverse interests.
Did you know his middle name was Loyola?
His name was literally Ignatius Loyola.
He might have been Roman Catholic.
Mike possibly.
Yeah.
It is you, at least.
Although I think he was a man of diverse interests.
Not exactly an Orthodox Roman Catholic.
And I think he was lapsed.
But.
Lieutenant Governor of Minnesota.
Man, yeah, he's pretty high political. He wrote a book. One of many things he wrote, but he wrote a book called Atlantis, the antediluvian world.
Yeah, he decides to just go all the way and pull this all together into one theory.
So he believed that Genesis really Genesis 1 through 6. Everything in Genesis before the flood was set in Atlantis.
Okay, so Adam and E. Board Lantians.
Yes, even that's why you can't find the Garden of Eden no more.
That's right.
It's it's on underneath the Atlantic Ocean.
Yes, it's sank into the Atlantic Ocean.
So all that was sitting at Lannis, all that happened at Atlantis.
And then, you know, the arc ends up over in, you know, the near east and things go from there.
He argues that that the sinking of Atlantis is the origin of all the flood stories.
He argues what we were just talking about with the minds and stuff.
That's where all the Native Americans come.
came from. And so the Atlantean culture after the flood, through flood survivors, gets scattered
across the whole world. Right. If any of you are familiar with Graham Hancock, this is where
he got his stuff. He's just a plagiarizer. He is, no, he's the modern Ignatius Donnelly.
I was a saint. Right. He's the modern Ignatius Donnelly. He's making a lot of the same arguments.
Yeah.
Um, so then things to take a dark turn.
You're ready.
You know, I have to say by the way, if you ever look up a photo of Ignatius,
Donnelly, he looks like Biff from the back of the future movies.
He kind of does.
He kind of, I'm looking up people out of the chats, looking up,
doesn't not look like Biff from the back to the future movies.
Um, think that's a, that I mean, that's a little weird.
It's kind of weird theorizing.
Not a lot of support for it, a little bit out there, but mostly harmless, right?
Mostly harmless.
It's not, then things go really awry because the person who then really sets in on these
theories and Atlantis in particular is Madame Blavotsky.
Oh man.
favorite occultist.
spiritualist. And yeah get ready. So she has this theory that in the history of the world
there was a succession of great races, sort of master races. Oh, I feel like I've heard that phrase
somewhere before who led the world in like culture the arts and everything.
And the Atlanteans were the previous one.
Guess who the current one is.
That's right. The Aryans.
What?
Yes. We're going into dark territory, folks.
And the Aryans, according to her, were descended from the Atlanteans.
They were descended from the Atlantean survivors, the Aryan race they were.
And therefore they had the anti-deluvian wisdom.
Yeah.
Babylon coming right back around again.
Now she, so what, less restrained than say the Ignatius Donnelly, says that let us sunk
one million years ago.
Man, we're way past Plato now.
Yeah.
Not 9,000, one million years ago.
Well, that's convenient because that's much harder to grab archaeologically speaking.
Yes, you know, yeah.
Well, yeah, harder to prove or disprove.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
She also... She's also...
the one who has the Atlanteans having psychic powers. Dark psychic force and
super advanced technology involving crystals and stuff. Oh man. Right? And of
course, part of her thing is since the Aryan race still has this knowledge,
right? You can get those psychic powers for yourself. You can learn to
manifest.
those if you're an Aryan. According to her. By her book, subscribe to her YouTube channel.
You know, she didn't have any of that. You could buy her books as they she totally would have.
If she were alive, join her Theasophic Society, which has repudiated all the racial elements we
were just talking about by the way. Oh, by now, um, not that there's a lot of theosophists
still running around, but ask your local
rose accruations. I mean, people hardly even join the free masons anymore. Yeah, little
alone. Yeah. So then, you might imagine the sort of folk, say, in central Europe in the
early part of the 20th century, who might find these ideas attractive. Yeah. And guess what
they did. They did find them attractive and they pulled these at Lannister's...
traditions, these are called Atlanta traditions together with this other weird set of traditions
about hyperborea, which if you know the, you know, that's the hyperborea would be the
upper north, the right, the extreme north, where they believe there was sort of this
Nordic area and race of giants.
In this lost ancient land of hyperborea.
that gets smushed together with the Atlanta stuff by a group called the Thule Society.
Yeah, which so Thule or you know Thule I think it is in Greek right was this mythical northern
island in classical myth but is also the name of a town in Greenland. So how about that?
Right? There you go. Right. And so they have, Thule Society has the Atlanteans being sort of
Northern European Uber mentioned.
Of course they are.
Kind of descended from giants.
And of course, they are the origin of the Caucasian race.
According to the Fool's Society of Germany, which, what about the Caucasus?
Does that everything you do with Caucasians?
No.
And yes, yes, the Fool's Society of this stuff is the origin of Nazi.
paganism. The national socialist, their particular version of a cult paganism that they practiced.
Guess what they weren't Christians? Oh, you're shocked. Stop, I tell you.
That comes from this by way of the fool society. The belief that there are the descendants of
ancient Atlanteans who had access to these occult powers and powers of the mind and this sort of thing.
And it says, it's still not the weirdest thing.
Well, yeah, yeah, I mean it's probably the darkest. This is the darkest part probably. It's definitely the worst part of this half. Yes.
There's the last the last cool Atlanta figure we have to talk about. I could believe I could believe father Andrew did know who Edgar Casey was. I had heard the name. I had heard the name, but that was kind of it.
So Edgar Casey, aka the sleeping prophet, another American,
was a fella who claimed through
throughout his life that he was a good Christian.
He came out of the stone-camble restoration movement.
That's what he grew up in.
Like Christian church disciples of Christ, church of Christ, right?
One of those groups.
But it was in a very early stage of that.
Because he died in 1945.
So we're talking about early 20th century.
So but here's the thing about it, your Casey.
He was called the sleeping prophet because he would have psychic visions while he was asleep.
Right.
Yep.
Like in dreams.
And when I say psychic visions, I mean like he would go to sleep and people would like
bring sick people in and he would diagnose their diseases and prescribe cures in his
sleep.
While he was napping, did you know that he was the founder of a nonprofit organization
called the Association for Research and Enlightenment.
There you go. I love that. He also taught Sunday school. So yeah, he saw it. It's a weird thing for like an American Protestant to be doing. I know. I know sleep visions and psychic stuff. But he also
So, pract- claimed that still have-
By the way, clear avoidance exists.
To have clear avoidance that he could exercise while asleep.
that allowed him to like mentally travel in time and space and see things, right?
Both like remote viewing type stuff and time travel, right?
And so he used that to construct this history of the world.
Now, unfortunately, and I apologize already for the people this will offend, which is all
all Zoomers and some millennials.
He, part of his history of the world was that there are five races of humans that he described
based on color.
Well, that being white, black, brown, red, yellow.
Yeah.
So the reason that doesn't horrify Boomers and Jet X people is that we all learned the
song Jesus loves the little children as kids.
Right.
Partake
that well of racism. But it didn't mention brown people just red and yellow black and white.
Yeah. Yeah. So I guess brown people, God didn't love according to them. I don't know.
But the worst part about Edgar Casey's version is he thought they were all created separately.
Oh, that is racist. And we're not related to each other. That's super racist and yes.
Yes.
A little bit problematic.
Sorry, Zoomers.
You may have had the two.
out for that because you couldn't handle it. You're a little more safe now. But didn't
he, didn't he predict that Atlantis would back? He not only gave the location of Atlantis.
Yes. Where it was because he could time travel back to it. But he said that in the 1960s,
whenever he died in 1945, he said that the 1960s, it would rise up out of the sea. And
so there were a bunch of new ages in the 1960s, like the age of Aquarius folks who
like
really thought it was going to happen.
Like that that we were like Edgar Casey DeVote's who go out there on boats and stuff.
Um, he also claimed that all of his claims about human history could be verified.
We're going right back to Plato here folks.
If people would just dig under the Sphinx, I knew it.
In Egypt there was a secret library down there that had texts confirming everything he said.
man and they still haven't gone there yet have they see but now right proves it right and you're
all assuming we'll like yeah it didn't rise out of the sea of the 1960s as far as we know but
last little bit for this half are you ready I'm ready what they did find near where he said
Atlantis was was the Bimini Road and if you don't know what the Bimini Road is as far
the other end is people.
like chocolate me what what is that?
It is an underwater rock formation.
That's a spicissy looks man made.
That's a spicissy looks like a man made paved road.
That's right.
Clearly built by Atlantian, which the devotees say is an
Atlantian trade road.
That's right.
So you can look up photos of it.
Sunken be on the Google machine.
All right, well, on that stunning bombs.
So we're going to take our second and final break for this
deluvian episode of the Lord's Spirit's Podcast.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of
the epistles of Saint Paul disconnected from any historical reality.
But Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
In Saint Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young surveys
Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox
Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles, which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in first-century Judaism, D. Young hopes to unsettle commonly held notions
and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his historical context.
Available now at store.enchantfaith.com
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com
We're back now with the lower
of spirits with Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question,
call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, we're back. I hope you all are having as much fun as I am on this this anniversary episode
of Lord Spirit's podcast. Father Stephen, we actually have a caller waiting for us and you're
never gonna believe what his name is.
You want to just throw out a guess?
Atlas.
It is not Atlas. That would have been pretty cool. No.
Casey.
No, no. It's Noah.
Oh, there you go.
Yeah, we have a Noah, so Noah. Welcome, Lord Spirit's podcast.
Maybe we should ask him to call him.
Yeah, I'm sorry to use the point that my name is not Atlanta.
But Noah, I mean, that's as bad as good as the name as you could get for calling into this episode.
Yeah.
Yes, and I have a question about Noah.
So it works out perfectly.
All right.
Lay it on us.
So I thought this question was gonna be a little obscure,
but then I was in the second half and I met Pete.
So my question is based on 17th century book
by William Winston.
And he postulates that Noah probably lived in China before
and then subsequently after the flood.
And then afterwards fathered the Chinese people
other sunscreen after the flood.
As far as that is necessarily the bulk of my question, but more relevantly, it seems like
NOAA has a lot of blood behind them.
A similar mythos really to Enoch and a lot of second-toubled Jewish literature and a lot
in later Jewish Christian and Islamic literature.
We, I guess you talk a lot about ENARC and later in the
Transition.
stuff. So I was curious to know if any of these traditions had weight, I guess, in the
faith because obviously we can pull things from the book of Enoch and say there's something
to be gained here. But you would already talk about, for example, Noah inventing healing medicines
in the book of Jubilee's or having mistaken visions in the Genesis pocket font. So I'm curious
to know if there's something about Noah post-Ruby and that.
that we can take away from the story.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I feel like I'm just gonna throw this out there, Father Steven.
I think that we should do an episode, you know,
about Noah in particular.
I don't know, just throwing that out.
You're just trying to get at A answering his question.
No.
Oh, we'll do it episode someday.
Don't worry about it.
Yeah, of course someday.
See, there you go.
Everyone who just thought that the podcast was gonna end
there, we'll just keep saying someday.
which can be something.
the next episode. Yeah, it could be next month or whatever. Yeah. Yeah, I had never heard
of William Wiston, but I see his book is called a new theory of the earth, which so I'm
not to check this out. I mean, there is there are all these kinds of interesting traditions
about Noah having obviously having anti-deluvian wisdom because he literally is the main figure
from before the flood within the Christian tradition.
And even if you read Jubilee's, I don't remember if this is in first enoc, but I remember in Jubilee's
The angels come to know in his sons and they teach them all of the medicine and stuff
That all this knowledge that was lost before you know because of the flood
Right, so I mean this is in a sense that this is the redeemed version of all of that
kind of stuff. You get you get in the pagan literature where you know demons are whispering and God keeps
years. So yeah, I don't know. I've never heard of the China stuff though. That's completely
new to me. Have you heard of this before Father Stephen? I've heard variations of it. Yeah.
But yeah, so I think with with no traditions, there's a couple of things. So like some of those
get referred to in the New Testament, right? Like Noah being called the preacher of righteousness.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You're not doing that in Genesis, right? But that
comes out of like Jubilee's and other traditions. So it kind of depends on what you mean by
bear weight in the sense that, and this is a lot of what we're going to be, this is a good
segue into what we're going to be talking about here in the third half. If by bear weight you mean
something like our historically accurate in the modern sense, then no.
If by bear weight you mean do those traditions surrounding Noah?
contain spiritual truths, things that are applicable to the Christian life,
things that are valuable, valuable ideas and concepts, right? To be applied to
the Christian life, then the answer is yes, right? But you've got to do a
little work in each case to do that, right? It's not, because it's not always
obvious because most of those traditions come out of narrative sources.
Meaning it's not like a treatise where it just says like, you know, Noah did XYZ go and do likewise, right?
Like it's
It's just describing things happening. Noah doing things things happening to Noah things being revealed to Noah Noah saying things and
There's some steps between
And you know reading that narrative and then interpreting it and then
What's the core here and then how do you apply that right? There's sort of several steps you have to work through
to get from
those traditions to the sort of relevance, the weight that you're looking for.
Yeah.
Is that clarified things a little bit for you Noah?
Yes.
Thank you.
Appreciate it.
We're going to be expanding on that idea of what I just said.
Yeah.
So.
Thank you, Father.
Good.
Good segue.
Alright, well, I mean, don't you think maybe we should talk about the Bible, Father Steven?
Yeah, because as always, third half is what we talk about the actual topic.
Two, almost two and a half hours in at now the topic of the episode.
But so the point was that the reason we structured this episode the way we did is that,
okay, now with this background of other flood stories, of the Mesopotamian flood traditions
that we talked about in the first half of that last-
the plantas, right, in the way that plays out, right, that we talk about the second half.
Those ideas, right, with those in mind, now let's look at the story in Genesis, right,
which on pretty much any accounting post dates the Mesopotamian flood stories, right.
the quote unquote, and no, I won't argue or discuss.
this, but the early date of the Exodus has it in the 15th century BC. The tablets we were
talking about in the first half are from the 16th, 17th century BC. So, talking 100 years
at least, at least, minimally, 100 years before Moses, those actual tablets were written,
that the story was come up with, but that was actual tablets that we physically have.
predate Moses at his oldest, the oldest date for Moses. And then potentially then if you'd date
Moses later, there's even a bigger gap. Meaning that Genesis 6 through 9 is written and read and heard
in a world that already has those other stories in it or those other versions of the story in it.
a world that is practicing a religion, practicing a culture, practicing a way of life that is informed by those stories in various ways.
Such that the story in Genesis 6 through 9 is directly interacting with those stories and with the ways in which those stories have colored and influence the view of God or the God's humanity etc.
humanity, etc.
etc. that come from those stories.
Yeah.
So, I was going to say, I think that's such an important point, which we've made a bunch
of times on this podcast, but I think it's worth reiterating at this point, which is
that if you take the Bible as a kind of isolated text that you're supposed to be getting everything
from that's not referring to anything else, then you're not...
reading it at the very least you're not reading it or hearing it the way that the people who originally did hear it and read it would have received it.
You know they receive these texts within the context of a culture that they were already part of.
Right. You know. Right. And Genesis starts with the creation of the world, but it wasn't written down at the creation of the world. Right. Right.
Right again, early date.
Right early date of Moses early state of Moses
Right, and if you want to say Moses wrote every word exactly as it is in the Torah
So and and then you want to take a really extreme younger creationist position
Okay, say you go in for that whole package
Right you go in for that whole package
There's still about three thousand years of history before Moses
Yeah, yeah
which is
almost as much history as there is after Moses.
Hmm.
Okay.
So that's a lot of history.
That's a lot of time elapsed.
That's a lot of things that happened, cultures that were formed, things that were written,
stories that were told before the beginnings of the Bible, the Torah, enters into the world.
Right?
You want to take the view, the Jewish view, the
Torah is eternal. Great. It doesn't enter into our world. Right where people can read it and hear it until Moses. Right.
At the absolute earliest. So anyway, you slice it. Right.
Genesis comes into a world that already exists and is already fully formed.
And is working within and against that backdrop.
So, first major point of comparison, right?
And you may have been kind of...
doing this in your head as we were talking about the other stories.
Cause of the flood.
Why is this flood coming?
Well Genesis has a very different answer.
Yeah.
Genesis says that the flood comes because of the wickedness of humanity.
Humanity is wicked.
Humanity is evil.
But there's more than that.
We've talked about before on the show, we see in Genesis and the chapters leading up to
the flood, especially
chapters four and five, that there's this downward spiral, starting with cane, right,
that spirals down to the flood of wickedness.
And then when we get to Genesis six verses one through four, and it talks about the Nephilim,
it talks about the great men of old, the men of renown, right.
And based on the stories we just read, right, who is that?
based on the stories we just talked about.
Giant.
God kings, sons of Poseidon, right?
Yep.
It's pretty clear.
It's pretty clear who that's referring to.
Yeah, I mean, in a lot of ways, this is kind of one of the original, as some of the
kids out there would call it, universal history stories.
Yeah.
You know, Genesis is doing universal history.
It's big and cherimum or whatever his name is.
Yeah.
The... The... The...
Right. And so, but I want to, I want to hammer on this a little bit, right?
That's not based on that understanding of what Genesis six versus one through four is saying
is not at all based on anything in first,
enic, anything in Jubilee's anything of the book of the giants,
anything in any of those apocryphal texts that come later.
That reading of Genesis is not based on those.
That reading of Genesis is based on
on the earlier versions of the same story that were already around when the Genesis story
is first being version of the story is first being told.
Yeah.
I mean, that's what they would have understood it to be talking about.
Those those second-temple Jewish texts are not retconning.
Yes.
What those second-temple Jewish texts are doing is they're preserving that original context
for us.
That's what tradition does.
Tradition preserves the original context in which a text was understood because times and places and things change.
Right? Cities fall. Language has changed. Right?
And so the average person walking around the United States today who picks up the Gideon Bible in the drawer at their hotel and reads Genesis 6, 1 through 4
I'm gonna have the idea when it's talking
about. Yeah, it just comes out of nowhere, right? And there's not a copy of the Autohausus
epic or Plato's Critias. Yeah, they should be in the drawer. Tell rooms, right? Okay. And
the same thing was true in the third century BC. That's why you write something like the
book of Enic to preserve that original context of interpretation after, because again, in
Thank you.
Third century BC, guess what?
Jewish people didn't have a copy of the Autorosses epic.
Yeah.
Right?
But the original hears did.
And so that context is preserved to preserve
the correct interpretation over time.
But our basis for understanding it that way,
it very clearly means that.
If you're familiar with these other stories,
there's no way you can think that the original readers
heard that and thought about the sons of Seth.
It's just not even plausible, but that's what the original readers are.
Right.
They would have understood, oh, you're talking about these demigods, these heroes, these God kings, who the pagans worship and have shrines to.
next to the shrines of their pagan gods who are supposed to be their children.
Right?
That's who you're talking about, and you're saying they're not heroes.
They're not these great founding figures. They shouldn't be worshipped. In fact, they were evil. They were tyrants. They were thugs.
Right? And they were so evil and so destructive on the earth that God had to send a flood to wipe them out.
So it's a complete inversion of the pagan story.
Before the flood it was not a golden age with advanced knowledge and technology.
It was a corrupt and...
age, ruled over by tyrants. This is why if you actually start reading the story in Genesis 5
in the genealogy of Seth, and when you get to the birth of Noah, the prophecy at Noah's birth
is that God is going to save the world, save the creation through Noah.
So what is he saving the creation from God in Genesis is saving the creation from humanity
Hmm
Humanity is created as the crown of creation
Bridging the material and spiritual worlds
Right in order that the whole created order might be saved through humanity
Right, Christ becomes a carnage as a human.
And then through humanity, the whole created order is saved.
But what had happened before the flood is the inverse.
Yeah, because of our relationship with creation, if we go off, then that messes up the creation.
Right.
Humanity had corrupted the whole of creation.
Until creation had to be saved from humanity.
And that could only be saved through a human who wasn't corrupt.
And so since this is the anniversary episode where we're doing the greatest hits, sorry
Calvinists.
Okay, Genesis 6 does not say all of humanity's thoughts were always evil all the time, including
Noah, but God chose to freely impute the righteousness of Christ to Noah.
ignore the fact that he was just
sinful as everyone else by his own good pleasure to save the world through Noah. That's not what the
text says. It says he was a righteous dude. He was alone righteous in his generation. He was the
only righteous man on earth. He was fundamentally different in his way of life than all the other people
living at the time. I'm not saying that's not through God's grace. Of course, it's through God's grace.
Of course, it's through his cooperation with God's grace.
But nevertheless, he is fundamentally...
different. Right. He is fundamentally different. That's basic to the story.
Story didn't work without that. Now, unfortunately, before we could go on, we have to talk about
another major detour when people talk about the flood. Yes. Was it global? Was it local? Yes,
That's the extent of the flood.
ink has been spilled of the evangelical world about this.
Oh, indeed.
Linky podcast.
Anybody who talks about the flood, this is the primary thing they talk about.
Just like what they talk about the Exodus, they tend to spend way more time on
the early date versus the late date and which they hold and why then they do on what
it means.
What is the story and what it represents and why it's important.
Yeah, but let's talk as if what's important about it is then it really happened number one
then it really historically happened at number two what the date was and who was the Pharaoh.
Yeah, which we're going to get into this, but those are the two least important things about the story
of the Exodus. Yeah, it's like actually, one of the things, I can't remember where I heard this
now, what someone once said, the least interesting thing about God is that he exists. Yeah, and yet,
That's the thing that most people argue about the most.
Yes, right?
Like, I'm not saying.
the Exodus didn't historically happen.
Right.
I mean, somebody was pharaoh at the time it happened.
I'm just saying, which one it was?
Least interesting and important thing.
Yeah.
We can talk about in terms of the Exodus.
But yes, so the flood gets detoured
into this whole extent of the flood.
Right?
And they'll say, well, look, look.
It says in the text that it covered the highest mountain.
So that means Mount Everett.
The water was over the top of Mount Everest.
Now, unless you're Mark Booth, Mark Booth is a nutter.
He said that it didn't quite cover Mount Everest
and that Nepalese civilization is the pre-flood civilization.
Wow.
Wow, well we're talking about cock-eyed
do age theories. But anyway, so that's about Everest, right? Like that's got to be it. So we
know exactly how much water because we can take the height of Mount Everest plus a few feet, right?
Yeah. And so that's exhibit A of why this whole discussion, this whole discussion, both sides,
Right? Is just pure modernism.
No one.
Not Moses, right? Not any of the people who originally heard or read the story of Genesis
had ever heard of Mount Everest. Or knew there was a Mount Everest or had been there anywhere near there.
Right? Okay. And what are the big proofs of that? If you look at the things they call mountains,
Like in the Torah,
that are like barely hills by our standards today.
Like, yeah.
They had never seen Mount Everest, okay?
So they are referring to Mount Everest.
Okay, okay, that's modernism, modernism, you're looking.
Oh, the highest mountain.
Well, we all know that the highest mountain.
This is the kind of people who give you the argument like,
Jesus says that the mustard seed
is the smallest of all the seeds,
but technically it isn't.
So see the Bibles of Lie.
Checkmate Christians.
Right. But the people who are doing the
about Everest thing are all like they're
they're conservative Christians, but
they're doing the same thing. Yeah.
Yeah. They're doing the same goofy science thing,
modern science thing. Right.
Your episode called How and How Not to Read the Bible.
Yeah. So a few hours on this.
If you ask, does Genesis 6th and I present the
flood is global or local? Okay.
the answer is
Neither.
Yeah.
Because, okay, is there a hint of presented as global?
Because no one involved thought the Earth was a globe.
Yeah.
There's no globe.
They had no concept that the Earth was a globe.
So they can't possibly have been talking about a global flood, because that's not how they
saw the world.
Okay.
So, was it local?
No.
Because they say everything is wiped out.
It's neither global nor local.
So what is...
positively what does the text describe? Well, if you read the flood story in Genesis and you read it in the context of Genesis, remember how we were talking about the message to Pythamian flood myths.
Pretty much all of them either did or seem to have been preceded by a creation story.
Yep.
That this is all sort of part of and we're sort of dependent on that creation story.
Right?
Same story in Genesis.
Genesis 6 through 9 is dependent on you having read 1 through 5.
In fact, as we just said, Noah's born and there's a prophecy about the flood and stuff in 5.
So we got at least include 5. Well, 4, you know, cane, canes line goes right up to the flood with Lamek.
Okay, so we've got include 4. Well, you're not going to understand what's going on in the beginning.
So we're getting a cane and able if you don't read chapter 3 in the exposure program. Right?
You got to, it's a unit. Okay. It happens in the context of the rest of Genesis.
Genesis 1.
God creates the heavens and the earth.
Day one, he starts with the heavens, right?
Light and dark.
Days two and three, he's putting the earth in order.
And what does he do?
He separates the waters above from the waters below.
And then he separates the dry land from the water.
And then days four, five and six, he populates the places he created.
the fourth day we're back in the heavens.
You got the sun moon in stars, right? And then days five and six, you got the air,
sea, and land animals. And that finally culminates in humanity, okay? So the flood doesn't affect
the heavens. The flood is about the earth, right? You don't read the flood story that the sun and
moon in stars fell out of the sky or anything, right? It's just affecting the earth. So days one and
for off the table right.
Humans and animals are being preserved in the ark, right?
So days five and six off the table.
Okay?
Days two and three.
How is the flood described?
The waters above come down.
The waters below come up.
The dry land is covered with water.
So what Genesis describes is God uncreating the world.
That's what Genesis has happened.
Because what are you left with?
your left with...
where we started at the beginning of the book of Genesis, the waters.
Yeah, and the waters covering the earth.
And instead of the Holy Spirit hovering over the waters, you have the ark.
This microcosm of creation, right, within the ark, floating on the waters.
So Genesis does not describe a global flood.
It does not describe a local flood.
It describes God uncreating the world.
then recreating it at the...
end. And that's why when the arc lands and people disembark, God gives Noah the same command
he gave Adam and Eve. Fill the earth and subdue it. Right? So you may have noticed, right,
that there were some
details from some of those flood stories that also show up like the whole releasing birds thing.
Yeah. Right? Or offering sacrifices, in the case of Genesis, obviously, their sacrifices offered
to Yahweh, not to the gods, right? But, right, but sacrifices being offered right after the boatlands.
Right? There's all these details. That's proof it's plagiarized.
They took that from the others.
stories. Well, no, right? So if you're
purpose in retelling a story and telling it a different way is to make certain points
of contrast with the original story, you also have to make it clear that you're telling
the same story. Yeah, if it's all contrasts, then it's a different story. Right? So you
You have to keep some of the details.
have to keep some of the details and some of the basic structure of the story the same,
so that the hearer knows you're telling the same story, so that they can compare it
to the way they've heard the story before and notice the differences, which differences
in your telling are what you're trying to communicate, right?
That's the vehicle for what you're trying to teach and communicate.
That's why we get some of these same details.
And notice again, we already commented on this a little bit, but this command, be fruitful
and multiply, right?
This is the exact opposite of what happens in Othrahasis, where Enlil and the other gods
try to limit the fecundity of humanity.
You have so much about this story is telling us who God is in contrast to who the pagan
gods are.
Yes.
and it's big.
It's an inversion.
Right? God wants to encourage reproduction and not only see
encouraging reproduction of the animals and humans.
Right? But within that he what prohibits murder?
Killing. We don't want people killing each other.
We don't want life to end prematurely. Right? That's God is pushing in the other
exact opposite direction. God is pro life of the pagan gods in
God's in after-hases.
And this even goes to the animal.
right because we get this stuff about eating blood here and I know this is a
misunderstood thing right because we tend to get it opposite we tend to read
this in the exact opposite logical order from what's actually going on in the
text so the logical order we read this in is okay God says it's okay to eat
animals. Why? Well, not totally sure. I mean, I guess you know...
they haven't had time to plant crops yet.
So maybe they needed the protein or something?
I don't know, but for some reason,
God finally gives them permission to eat animals
and says it's okay, which makes it okay.
And then he says, but don't eat the blood though.
Okay.
Don't eat the blood though.
And so people got to puzzle over it.
That's because that's a reverse logical
order. Here's the actual logical order of what's going on in Genesis. And this is drawn out in all the ancient commentaries on it.
It's the exact opposite order. Okay, what was the problem that caused the flood? The problem that caused the flood was human sin.
Specifically, human sin is it corrupted and twisted and destroyed creation.
So we have to do something about that so that we don't get a situation like before the flood again.
We need to manage that sin in the corrupt
of creation. How do we do that? We do that through a tonement. That's what a
tonement is. It's the purification of the created order from human sin and its
effects. How do we do that? Well, to do that, we need blood. Right? You do that
with blood. Blood is life stuff. Get rid of the death stuff. Okay? So we need
animal blood. Well, how are we going to get animal blood? Right? How do we...
get animal blood to do that with, sort of pure animal blood. Well, you would get that from
a sacrifice. Okay, that means we're going to have to sacrifice animals to get the blood
to do the atonement to stop the flood. Okay, so we've got to sacrifice animals. So if
we're going to sacrifice animals, then people need to be able to eat the animals so they
could participate in the sacrifices. So humans are allowed to eat animals in Genesis
because they need to sacrifice animals and they need to sacrifice animals so they can get
blood.
And they need to get the blood so they can make a tonement for sin to keep the situation
from before the flood from happening again.
That's the logic of what's going on in Genesis about killing the animals.
And so if you kill an animal and don't sacrifice it, it offers some to God, or you kill an
animal and sacrifice it, but consume the blood.
Right?
As those cases you can't use
the blood for atonement. And so you've taken that blood for no reason. You've taken the
life of that animal for no reason. What justifies the taking the life of the animal is using the
blood for atonement. That's the logic of Genesis. That's the logic of Genesis. Why then you
might ask do we are we still not allowed to eat blood as Christians? Which if you've read
X15 you should know.
Right? Right? Because we're not using animal blood for atonement anymore.
Because Christ's blood kind of took care of the need for that, right?
We still don't eat blood because that blood is still reserved for that purpose,
even though we're not using it for that purpose. So since we're not using it for that purpose,
we use it for no purpose.
We drain it into the ground.
is what you're supposed to do with it. Right? You return it to the earth for which the animals came
because you're not using it for a tonne anymore because you don't need to.
But you don't eat it. Right? You don't eat it.
And so finally, finally, and this is kind of the core question that we were getting at a few minutes
to go in this half.
Is the Genesis story of the flood historical?
Yeah, right? That's really putting a fine point on the question.
Beyond even asking its extent, is it historical?
Now, we have to say a couple things about that.
Okay. So, first of all,
The text of Genesis does not have a historical purpose.
What do we mean by this?
I mean, a text with a historical purpose would be like,
if I went and did a bunch of research, and I found out that something happened in my hometown
50 years ago that nobody knows about.
Okay? And I wrote a book about it.
That book would have a historical purpose my goal in writing the book is I want people to
know about this thing that happened that they don't know that it happened.
Okay? That's what I mean by a historical purpose. If I go and I write a book on the Civil
War right now, right, the American Civil War, it's not going to be with the purpose of
telling people that America had a Civil War in the 1860s. Everybody kind of knows that,
Right, and if I wrote the book from the perspective
of, hey, none of you know this, but there was this guy McLean, right?
Like people would look at the book and be like, what is this garbage?
I've read 57 books on the American Civil War, right?
What is with this guy?
Right?
This is like babies for civil war book.
Right.
If I wrote a book on the Civil War now, which there's lots of other retellings
of the story of the Civil War out there, then I would have some other point beyond
just telling you that
that it happened, or telling you this is what happened.
I would be focusing on something, some element of it,
maybe that I thought wasn't emphasized,
or I would be telling some particular stories within it
with some aim, or to suggest like,
I think X was actually the cause of the war rather than Y.
Or I think X was the deciding factor in Y, the North one,
Sorry locals.
Rather than why.
Right, I would be saying something about the American Civil War. I would not just be arguing that it happened.
Because no one would be arguing back that it didn't.
Yeah, and it's because the context is
everybody knows the story or something about it.
Right. And so when I say the Genesis story isn't trying to tell you that a flood happened and wiped out
everyone except a family and some animals in a boat.
That's not its purpose. I mean, that's not its purpose because all of the original readers and hearers already knew that story.
They'd already heard that story. That was for them common knowledge. They just considered that to have be a thing that happened in the past.
So, when Genesis tells that story, it's not for the purpose of trying to convince people
that this really happened and happened in a certain way.
Right. It's about saying something about those events. Yeah, because there's that hasn't
been said. A good amount of evidence with a lot of these details in the exact same regional
neighborhood that you know, the Israelites are living in. So yeah, one of the chances.
And this is fundamentally how ancient theology was done.
Yeah, right? This is how you did ancient theology. It was done in narrative form. You told a story that was not a brand new story you made up.
You told a story, the more familiar the better, but you told it in a different way with a different emphasis focusing on different figures, right? And by the way you told it, you reoriented how people saw themselves, God or the gods.
the world, the past, right, where that was leading into the future, right?
You reoriented that by retelling the story in a new way, right?
So it's not about arguing about the details.
If you got, you know, uh, uh, I was about to say epinema.
It's back.
Um,
But if you got our friend, Epikaya, right?
And you sat him down with Moses and they both told their version of the story, right?
They would see how they would disagree if they had a conversation about it.
The conversation would not be like, wait, what kind of bird did you say it was?
What shape did you say the boat was?
That's not what they would they would
be quibbling over the details. Only one of these can be true. They would be talking about
bigger issues. They would say, so you're saying that the most high God loves humanity and
wants to see it flourish. Whereas I have always believed that humans are slaves to the
right? That's a big difference. That's the core of what the stories are aimed at.
Those would be the things they would be discussing.
Right?
Not the details.
And which is true, right?
And this is important, not,
I mean, the flood story here is an example we're using.
But this applies to the whole way we interpret
any narrative in the Bible up to and including the gospels.
Okay?
When the dumb dumb atheist comes to you and says,
Well, which is it, were there two angels out there?
the tomb or one inside the tomb. It can't be both the whole Bible's a lie. It contradicts itself,
right? Aside from laughing at him, right? Don't scoff or mock though, those are bad in the Bible.
Um, right? You need to point out like you don't get it man. That's not how this works.
Okay, like
Say it's Matthew, Mark and Luke, are not trying to convince you that Jesus rose from the dead
by getting all of these details right and consistent.
They're trying to communicate things to you about
the resurrection of Jesus and
what it means
and why it is of preeminent importance
and the details that they use or leave out or put in.
right are all in service of the point they're trying to make about what they're
describing. They're not just trying to give some objective narrative
accounting of here are the events that happened in order right and I hate to
tell you, but it's almost impossible to do that.
I hate to David Hume at you, right?
But there's a deep cut reference.
But you can't see cause and effect.
So as soon as you say X caused Y in a narrative,
you've entered into the realm of interpretation
and subjectivity.
To be quote unquote objective,
it would have to be this happened,
then this happened, then this happened.
But even that narrative,
you're talking from a person.
perspective. You have it narrated every single thing that happened. Just some of them,
there's subjectivity again. You're saying something about it. You're not just communicating
that it happened and that it happened in a particular way. So, in the same way, if you
got Matthew, St. Matthew, Mark and Luke, you got it together in a room. They wouldn't sit
they're arguing about how many angels there were at the tomb and where they were positioned.
They'd be sharing the evisities of things that they wanted thought were important most important to say
about the resurrection of Christ or about his death or about his teaching
Right, none of them are trying to argue this is exactly what happened in this order in exactly this way
Well, we've reached the end of
episode on the flood. And I imagine probably a lot of you were thinking, well, what about,
you know, all these other flood stories that exist up in North America, stuff in other
parts of the world and so forth. And I mean, we could do that endlessly. But I wanted
to talk about one that I think weirdly maybe a lot of people don't know too much about.
So I want to talk about the flood story as it is told.
in the prose edda by Snorri Sturelson, that Icelandic writer who is the scribe of much of
what we know about Norse mythology. Snorri was a Christian and, you know, he lived probably 200 years
after the baptism of the last Norse pagan. He never met a Norse pagan in his life. There weren't
to numerous bigons around.
So anyway...
If you read the beginning of the prose at a, you'll get the flood story as exists in Norse mythology.
So I'm going to just kind of retell it to you briefly, in case you don't know it.
There is a sort of primeval giant named Emir and Odin and his two brothers, Vylian Vey,
the sons of Bohr, they decide to kill Emir.
And so when they kill him, there's so much blood that flows out of his wounds that
it drowns all of the race of the frost giants.
So it kills giants.
So you can see already there's a big continuity here
between the biblical story and the other stories
we talked about, you know, giant, a big flood,
killing lots of giants.
And then the story goes on where that Odin
and Vilien Vey, they take the body of Emir,
this premieval giant out into what is called Ginnogongap,
which is kind of this big void,
and they take parts of his body
and the world is created from it, right?
So his body basically,
his main part of his body becomes the earth,
his blood becomes the sea, the lakes,
the flesh and the rocks of his bones become the mountains
and the hills and the land, you know,
his teeth and become the stones and sort of this stuff.
And then
His skull is used to make the sky, his brains are thrown up to make the clouds.
It kind of goes on and on like this.
And so this is massive dismemberment of this giant that becomes the world.
But there's an interesting detail in here that I skipped over on purpose because I wanted
to cover it last and that is there is a survivor.
There is a survivor of the flood, right?
And so here's what the text actually says.
It says,
BORS SONS KILL THE GIANT EMIER.
And when he fell...
so much blood flowed from his wounds that with it they drowned all the race of frost giants.
Except that one escaped with his household. Giants called him Birgul Mir. He went up onto his
ark with his wife and was preserved there, and from them are descended the families of frost giants.
As it says here, and now it's quoting what's called the poetic edda or a text related to it,
But countless winters before the Earth was created, then was Berk-
mirror-borne, that is the first I remember when that wise giant was laid on a box. And
there's more that goes on about the creation of the world from the body of emir. But I
wanted to focus on Bergelmir, a second here. So Bergelmir is essentially the Noah figure
in the Norse telling of the flood. But you see, he's not a human. He's not one of the gods
either he's a giant.
Now what is relationship between giants and the gods?
If you go by what it's written in the Edas,
either the prose or the poetic,
at a, the line between the two is pretty fuzzy.
There's a whole lot of intermarriage
between the giants and the gods,
which is kind of what you'd expect
if you know anything, for instance, about,
What we said about giants in our seventh
episode now almost five years ago that there's this kind of intermingling going on.
Although in this case, there's no humans involved.
And I think that's really notable is that the one who is saved in this flood is not Noah,
a human, a righteous human, but rather burglar mirror this giant.
And then it says that from him is descended the families of Frost Giants.
So all the frost jansk killed by this big
bloody flood, except this one guy who then repopulates the world with frost giants.
And as far as I recall, Berglmeer never shows up again in Norse myth.
There might, I don't know, he might get mentioned in Asaga somewhere or something like this.
I'd have to go look.
So he's actually a pretty bit character in all of this, but it's notable that he's the father
of all the frost giants that exist post-flood slash creation of the world, because it's
It's kind of the same thing.
in the Norse myth. Why point this out? Well, in Norse myth, the difference between the
gods and the giants is kind of the gods are the good guys and the giants are the bad guys.
That's sort of how it sort of shakes out in these stories. And in the end of the world,
Ragnarok, which means the twilight of the gods, there'll be a big battle between the
the gods and the giants and the monsters come out and they're all of course on the side of the
giants and what's the difference between a monster and a giant?
Eh, hard to tell.
And the gods all get killed and many of the giants and monsters die as well.
And the world kind of resets.
This is a very different story than the one that's told in the scriptures.
And I want to especially note that the one who's saved in the scriptures by God,
this righteous man is precisely a human being.
Right, we've under...
a number of times in this episode, the difference between the way that Yahweh, the God of Israel,
comes across in the biblical flood story versus the way that the various gods of the nations
come across in their own stories. Right? Now, like the epic of Gilgamesh, the, you know, all of these
stories that we've mentioned, this is not propaganda by Christians or Israelites about pagans.
These are the pagans telling their own stories, okay? So that they're telling you who their gods are
by the way that the guy's
behave in their stories that they themselves wrote. So, you know, we've seen this contrast.
One of the things we haven't really underlined, though, is that Noah, and I do hope that we do
a Noah episode, but that Noah contrasts also significantly with the person, or in many cases,
God or God-king or future immortal, future God, that is the one that's on the
boat in these various stories. And of course, we just mentioned that in the Norse myth, it's a giant,
it's quite literally a monstrous figure who is the one who kind of rides out the flood in his
big boat along with his wife. Noah is not just saved by God. Noah becomes a new father of the
human race. He becomes in a sense another atom, right? And he is this preacher of righteousness. He's
helping
to reset humanity to begin things well again, if possible. Now we know of course that things
go badly again after this. But Noah is this figure of salvation. He's the one through whom
God is saving the human race. Ultimately, this points us to Jesus who is not just a man who
rises up as the righteous one in the midst of a very dark.
and faithless world and dark and faithless generation, right?
But is also God.
So Christ is the one to whom all of these stories
are actually pointing,
the one that's really doing it right.
And even though he's not riding out a literal flood,
there is nonetheless the world is full of darkness and sin
and is dominated by demons.
That's the world into which Jesus is
B-
And he is the one who is regenerating the human race in and of himself. He is the true second and new Adam.
Noah is a forerunner of Christ in that sense.
And so I think that to understand the flood correctly is also to understand something about
who Jesus is.
That's why it's absolutely the case that all of human history not just is relied history all of human history including the pagan histories.
All find their fulfillment their end their purpose.
In Christ.
And so as we like to occasionally say in this podcast, you know, this isn't just about crazy weird.
Giant lore or flood lore or whatever even though of course we enjoy the nerdy tour through.
you know, click
tablets one can find stuck on a shelf in the British Museum or in the you know
UPEN Museum in Philadelphia it really is about Christ and that's where we should arrive and I
think that this is one of the stories that shows us how the awesome arc of human history
finds its rest its purpose its fulfillment in the Lord Jesus.
Father Stephen.
Sorry, I started snoring when I heard snory snorkels and thank you very much.
So one of the things that if you listen to much of my stuff or read books, I've written
and stuff, one of the things I have around all the time is the importance of understanding
what often gets translated as faith and
and far worse than that belief in the New Testament and the Bible in general, understanding
that is actually being about faithfulness.
That may not seem related to what we were talking about tonight at first, but it's deeply
related because part of the watering down of faithfulness into just belief, just thinking
some
thing is true. Mentally assenting to the truth of something has been the wrecking of our modern
ability to read and understand the scriptures. What's happened is that sort of affirming the
historicity and particular details of the historicity of different things found in the Bible have
become this whole
series of chivaleths that mark out who is the real Christian and who is not. I was at
a Protestant ordination exam once, where this was the oral exam. I tried to decide, are
Are we going to ordain this guy as a minister or not?
They only asked him one question.
And that was, do you believe that Jonah was really swallowed by a fish?
That was it!
And if he said, yes, I mentally assent to the idea that in roughly the early 8th century
BC, a man named Jonah who was a prophet of God was swallowed by a fish, oh, you, sir, are
fit to be a minister.
to lead people to salvation. But if you say no, that you don't take that totally
literally the way we'd like you to, then you are unfit to do that. Requested whether you
are a Christian at all. Let me tell you that is preposterous. And let me also, right,
This isn't just me bashing certain types of evangelical Protestant, okay?
This happens in the Orthodox Church too.
Maybe especially in America, but I don't know that for sure.
Maybe more ubiquitous than that.
We're certain things.
Back of the day, I'm glad this is in the case,
we're rather as, do you leave the literal toll houses?
That's what marked a real Orthodox version from a...
Do you mentally ascend to this idea that this is true?
But some of the bug bears that are true across the board are things directly related to the kind of stuff we were talking about tonight
Was it a global flood
It literally happened exactly this way are those the literal dimensions of the arc
How old is the earth who was the Pharaoh at the time of the Exodus when did it happen?
right
And it's all in this...
mental ascent. If you don't mentally ascent to the idea that see it orthodox circles,
it's interesting because the orthodox circles, it's, oh, the earth is 7,500 years old because
like the weird internet high mind has decided that's what all the fathers say, which isn't
what all the fathers say, but that's what all the fathers say. Even though 7,500 is not
the number you come up with the Bible, it's not worth. Promise it, younger creationist
think it's about a thousand years younger than that.
If you don't ascent to that, if you don't say yes, this is true, then somehow you're
not really orthodox.
You're not really a Christian.
Here's the thing.
That's not what believing something means.
Because again, it's not belief, it's faithfulness.
So it has to do with how you live your life.
So if someone comes to me and tells him,
they believe in evolution.
They believe in human evolution.
Okay.
The question I have for them is essentially
what do you mean by that?
Because if what they mean by that is
I learned about this in school,
seems plausible to me,
seems to be what reasonable people think.
I mentally ascend to the idea that,
yeah, millions of years ago that happened.
I don't care.
It's a rel
of it. Believe whatever you want, right? Believe there are witches in the woods, right?
But believe that there's a pink unicorn in your backyard. It's irrelevant. It's relevant.
Now if what I say, what you say to me when I say, what do you mean by you believe in evolution
is I believe that this world, in this world, it's survival of the fittest. I believe
it.
the strong survive, the strong should take from the weak.
The weak should know their place.
Right? I look down on people who are poor.
I look down on people who are weaker than me.
I look down to people from other races.
I look down on people from other cultures.
I look down on people who in general aren't like me.
And I think I have the right being a better person,
a smarter person, to take from them.
Right?
Now...
I'm concerned. Why? Because living your life that way, you're not going to find salvation.
You're going to find quite the opposite. Now I'm concerned. Now I'm worried. That's a person who
believes in evolution. And guess what? A person who says they think the earth is 6,000 years old,
but who acts like that believes in evolution.
You don't find out what someone believes by what they say.
You find out...
what someone believes by what they do. What someone does, what they're faithful to, the
ideas that they use in their life and put into action, that they play out, that's what
they believe. And this is basic, right? If someone comes to me, right, and they tell me,
you know, oh, hey, I've got this plan and that plan and that next year, I'm going to do
this, I already bought the plane tickets, I'm doing this and that, and then they say to me
Oh yeah, my doctor told me I've got two months to live.
I'm gonna be like, clearly you don't believe your doctor.
Right?
Because you wouldn't be making all these plans for next year.
These long-term plans, if you really thought you were gonna die in two months.
Right?
If you actually believe it, it will affect how you live and what you do.
because belief is about faithfulness, not just ascending to an idea.
It's about what you act out in your life.
And some of these things that I don't care about at all, like the date of the Exodus, it's
because it makes no difference.
It makes no difference in the Christian life of actual people.
Real people, which is all of you, all of you listening, are actual people.
You are not AI's.
or actual people who every day have
to make decisions and after struggle with things, struggle with temptations, struggle with
desires that you need to not act upon.
Right?
Struggle to do it is right.
Struggle to love people who aren't necessarily completely lovable to you all the time.
Struggle to work out your salvation.
All of us, myself included, need a lot of help with that every day, moment to moment.
Knowing who was Pharaoh during the Exodus does nothing to help with that.
And nothing to harm it either. It's irrelevant. It's not important.
But understanding, for example, in the Exodus, that God led his people out of slavery and
led them from death to life. And that your life, right, that is a microcosm of your life,
God leading you out of slavery to sin, breaking the chains of sin.
setting you free, leading you through death into new life. Right? That's something
I need to hear. That's something that's going to help me with those struggles.
Right? Understanding, right, that God, right on point with what we talked
about night, tonight, understanding that God didn't create me to be his slave.
that God doesn't find me annoying.
That God isn't irritated and angered by me
and is likely to destroy me as to leave me alone.
Knowing that that's not God, but that God instead loves me.
That He wants me to flourish.
That He wants me to grow, that He wants me to have life.
That's something I need to know.
not exactly when and exactly where and exactly what the extent of the flood was.
That doesn't help me. That doesn't help me at all.
So that's what I'm getting at when I say there are some things that I just don't care about
and that we're not going to discuss on this show and you're not going to hear me discussing my Bible study very much.
Right.
There have been a few times where I talk.
some of this stuff in academic settings that I had to talk about those things a
little bit because it was an academic setting but for the most part I don't
care it's not relevant to real people in their real lives and even though I've
got a PhD and even though there's all kinds of stuff I love to talk about I talk
about even more wide range of stuff on my Twitch stream I'll talk to you
about comic books and movies and TV shows and video games and all kinds of
stuff, right? But that's...
those are the things I consider really important.
At core, I am a priest.
A person who God has given the solemn responsibility
of trying to help other people find salvation.
And here's the thing with being a priest, right?
Pretty much any other job where you're trying to lead people
towards something, it's something you've already achieved
for yourself, right?
Like if you signed up for an exercise course
and you were paying...
money and I came out to be your instructor, you'd leave and demand a refund.
Because you'd be like, this guy doesn't know what he's talking about exercise.
What? Right? Fortunately, my parishioners don't have that reaction when I serve
literature. Right? Because I'm trying to lead them towards salvation and I'm
still working on mine. Some of them are ahead of me. That makes it really hard when
you're a priest. And you've got people who are your spiritual children who are
more pious and further along the road to God than you, more Godly than you.
But that's my job.
And so while some of this other stuff is fun to talk about, and cool, and nerdy, and like talking about, it's not what's important.
It's not what's really important.
And so for this show, for my Bible study and stuff, right, aside from some jokes, some aside, some presentation, right,
So I'm just trying to hook people in some rhetorical stuff, right?
Our real focus is on the stuff that's important and the stuff that counts.
That's why we're not going to talk about the age of the year.
That's why we're not going to talk about the data to the Exodus.
That's why we're not going to talk more than I already did today about JEDP.
Right? Or any of that stuff. We're trying to reconcile the details of the gospel accounts.
Because this is just not important.
So focus on what's important. And when you focus on what's important,
then the scriptures, the liter
the hymns, the writings of the fathers, that'll all open up to you because you'll be asking the right questions.
You'll be trying to get the right things. You won't get distracted.
That's what I got to say.
Amen. Well, that is our fifth anniversary show. Thank you everyone very much for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsonationFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook page
Okay.
or you can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find that parish,
out here in the 3D world, head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
Join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific.
Why is the world in love again? Why are we marching hand in hand?
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page, you can join our discussion group.
Leave reviews and ratings in all the appropriate places, and don't forget to share this show with a friend.
And finally be sure to go to www.exrefate.com.stokesupport and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Why are the ocean levels rising up?
It's a brand new record for 1990.
Thank you, good night and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord.
of spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father
Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands
of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power,
riches and wisdom and strength and honor.
Glory and blessing Revelation chapter 5